<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eclogarius, or briefe summe of the truth of that title of Supreame Governour given to his Maiestie in causes spirituall, and ecclesiasticall, from the Kings of Israel, in the old Testament; the Christian emperours in the Primitive Church; confirmed by 40. epistles of Leo the Bishop of Rome, vnto the Emperours, Theodosius, Martianus, and Leo. Not published before. By Iohn Panke.</title>
            <author>Panke, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08890</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106400</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842117</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842117</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6746</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08890)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6746)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 585:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Eclogarius, or briefe summe of the truth of that title of Supreame Governour given to his Maiestie in causes spirituall, and ecclesiasticall, from the Kings of Israel, in the old Testament; the Christian emperours in the Primitive Church; confirmed by 40. epistles of Leo the Bishop of Rome, vnto the Emperours, Theodosius, Martianus, and Leo. Not published before. By Iohn Panke.</title>
                  <author>Panke, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 62, 79-88+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Joseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: The truth of the oath of supremacy.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks quire E and all after page 88; trimmed at head, affecting headline.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6746:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6746:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ECLOGARIVS,</hi> OR BRIEFE SVMME OF THE TRVTH OF THAT Title of Supreame Governour, given to his Maieſtie in cauſes Spirituall, and Eccleſiaſticall, from the Kings of Iſraell, in the old Teſtament; the Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours in the Primitiue Church; confirmed by 40. Epiſtles of Leo the Biſhop of Rome, vnto the Emperours, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius, Martianus, and Leo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not publiſhed before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> IOHN PANKE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gratian decrees, Cauſa 23. Quaeſt 5. cap. 20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Let the Princes of the world knowe, that they of duty ſhall render an account to God for the Church which they haue taken of Chriſt to preſerue. For whether the Peace and diſcipline be increaſed, by faithful Princes, or it be looſed, he doth exact of them an accompt, who hath delivered his Church, to be committed to their power.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by Joſeph Barnes, 1612.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6746:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6746:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO</hi> THE CHRISTIAN REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whether Proteſtant, or <hi>Romiſh Catholike.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE queſtion of late riſen ſince his Maieſties raigne, (Chriſtian Reader, whether Proteſtant or Romiſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like) are eſpecially now about the <hi>oath of allegiance,</hi> made in Parlament, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by his Maieſtie and the ſtate, to be taken by every Subiect for the ſecurity of his Highnes perſon and life, if ought ſhould be intended againſt him. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions againſt the ſaid <hi>oath,</hi> are iuſtly none, but only a commandement there is from the Pope in his Breues, forbidding the Romiſh Catholike the taking thereof. Now becauſe his Maieſtie himſelfe,<note place="margin">In his Apologie for the oath of allegiance.</note> hath in a Princely care of ſatisfying his ſubiects of his intent therein, and Prieſtly iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6746:3"/>laid open himſelfe &amp; confuted thoſe Breues,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iallude to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantines Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munis Epiſcopus</hi> Euſeb de vit. Conſt. l 1. c. 37. <hi>Pope Paule,</hi> 5.</note> needles it is for any man after him, further to write in defence of what he hath iuſtified. But ſince the pretence of the Pope in his Breeues, and of Bellarmines letter to the Arch-prieſt Blackwell, was to inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate that vnder colour of ſwearing to the oath of allegiance, they ſhould bee forced that tooke it, to ſweare ſomething againſt the Popes ſupremacie <hi>in spirituall matters,</hi> which being not by that oath intended, his Maieſtie hath in an holy and painefull regard, to ſatisfie thoſe, whom any thing would ſatisfie, ſet his pen to paper againe, acknowledging the former worke to bee his owne, and added thereto <hi>a premonition to all Chriſtian Monarches, free Princes and States,</hi> containing moſt ſweet doctrine of his owne faith; beſides many plaine evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, that the Pope is Antichriſt; holding the ſame intent in both; proveth ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently in both, that thoſe two oaths haue their contrarie ends, and are nothing like each to other, and that they who take the one, are not therefore charged with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The like anſwer againe receiued Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine from the Archprieſt,<note place="margin">Mat. Tortus calling himſelfe Bellar. chaplen but was Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himſelfe.</note> in defence of his taking the ſaid oath; as alſo Bellarm. vnder the name of
<hi>Tortus</hi> firſt, and of Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6746:3"/>after, from the Reverend Biſhop of Ely. Now becauſe in this conflict be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Church of Rome and vs, for this later oath of allegiance,<note place="margin">The oath of allegiance.</note> that former of his Maieſties <hi>ſupremacie in spirituall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> ſhould neither lie forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as though it were not, nor be miſtaken through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance by thoſe who vnderſtand it not; I will (becauſe perhapps to me is miniſtred ſome ſpeech thereof, which to others is not) ſhew all men out of the true records of all antiquitie the truth &amp; equity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; That as in this laſt, his Maieſtie requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth nothing of the takers thereof, but ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for him and his (as by an oath of true allegiance) againſt thoſe that ſhall ſeek his life: ſo in the former, hee intendeth to v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpe nothing in <hi>spirituall and eccleſiaſtical matters,</hi> that is, <hi>belonging to the Church:</hi> but to practiſe that power, which the Godly kinges of Iſraell in their times about the ſame matters; and the moſt Chriſtian and beſt Emperors of the world ever practiſed and vſed in all their daies; thereby to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all forraine power and iuriſdiction, which any Prelate, Prince, or Potentate, ſhal execute, or promote in his dominions; the ſafty of taking both oathes, and the truth of both being both alike. Much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6746:4"/>I confeſſe hath formerly bin beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and many treatiſes written by worthie,<note place="margin">Defence of the Apology by B. Iuell, part. 6. B. Horn againſt Fecknam. B Bridges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Staplet. counter blaſt. B. Wincheſter that now is in his Dialogues. D. Rainolds co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with Hart, part. ult. Tortura Torti. <hi>Vincent. Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinenſis cont. haereſ. c. 27. Eadem quae didiciſti, ita doce ut cum dicas nove, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dicas, nova.</hi>
               </note> and reverend men in this famous king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, touching the explication and expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the ſaid oath, ſome whereof ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving long ſince paſſed, and others at this preſent publiſhed in latine; the former, thoſe it concerneth will not now pervſe, as breeding forſooth faſtidiouſneſſe; the other in latine through their owne diſabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie ſome of them cannot take any profit by; ſo that I am in good hope onely by a few new collections in few ſheets of paper to win both their attentions, though not to a new matter, yet ſet downe in a newe maner. Further I am taught by the wiſe, that in a time of danger to the Church, it is not amiſſe, that many though ſome of them bee but meanely qualified ſhould write, for although they write all of the ſame things, yet may it bee in other forme and words; And that it is neceſſarie, that an adverſarie ſhould know,<note place="margin">Bellarm. in the the preface to the reader, in his <hi>1</hi> Tom. and <hi>1</hi> controv. out of Auguſtine.</note> that in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary campe there are not one only or two, but many that dare incounter with them. This commoditie beſides commeth of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny writing, that quicklier and eaſier our books may come to the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of all, though not all to every one, yet one or other to al
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6746:4"/>and ſo every man ſhall bee furniſhed with ſome thing. And to ſay the truth, I haue a deſire to draw on the Papiſt in this, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer beyond his ordinary gloſſe<note place="margin">Old Teſtaments warrant.</note> For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the hiſtory of the olde Teſtament giue abſolute and vnevitable grounds for warrant of what we ſeeke;<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſticall hiſtories.</note> The Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal hiſtories for 600. yeares &amp; better after Chriſt, in the beſt times of the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperours giue proofe of what his Maieſtie doth: yet am I willing herein to preſſe them with a witneſſe without excep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Leo the great Pope of Rome floriſhed anno <hi>440</hi> In his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius, Martianus, Leo to the Emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſes Pulcheria Eudocia. Eudo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xia, in folio, an. <hi>1569.</hi>
               </note> from whom by them, lyeth no appeal, and doe adiure them, by the honour they would ſeeme to beare to that ſea, whereof he was Biſhop, to ſpeake plainely and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to tell me, after they haue conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the true ſtate of the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſome other premiſes; whether hee in this ioyne not with vs, &amp; giue to the Emperors in his time by his letters as much, as we ſtriue for or his Maieſtie taketh to himſelfe in this buſineſſe, whereof we entreat. If he doe I craue but their aſſent to that oath; if he do not, their iuſt exceptions againſt the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence which is drawne from him. A ſhew of an anſwere to the moſt preſſing argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments brought by vs, I knowe hath beene ever ready from them; but ſuch that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6746:5"/>from none of them;<note place="margin">Read D. Mort. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; <hi>2.</hi> part of his Apologie, &amp; his Catholik ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſtants, and M. White of the way of the true Church.</note> an other hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermore bin readie to oppugne it, a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt evidence of a falſe ground. Thoſe eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and trickes on their parts, I wiſh in this excellent temper of the world, &amp; light of knowledge in the guids of this Church, whoſe eies they cannot blinde with any craft, were wholy laid aſide; and that the direct voice of Scripture firſt; ancient Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall hiſtories, for the practiſe of the chriſtian Emperors, and teſtimonies of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers confirming their practiſe, might bee called in. For in theſe caſes to anſwere of our ſelues is to anſwer nothing; not to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the allegation, is ſilently to graunt our adverſarie what he would. To bee ſo conceited to our cauſe, that whatſoever is tendered, not to ſee it, is willingly to caſt our ſelues headlong into the gulfe of end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe woe and miſerie. To come therefore to the firſt thing required, which is the oath it ſelfe, that al men may ſee what they ſweare vnto, that ſweare vnto it. The te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor where of is this. <hi>I.A.B. doe vtterly teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and declare in my conſcience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The oath of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie, in his Maieſties Apol. pag <hi>48.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that the kings highneſſe is the only ſupreame gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of this Realme, &amp; all other his Highnes dominions and countries, aſwell in spirituall or Eccleſiaſticall things or cauſes, as tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6746:5"/>And that no forraine Prince, perſon, Prelate, State, or Potentate, hath or ought to haue any iuriſdiction, power, ſuperioritie, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence, or authoritie Eccleſiaſticall, or spirituall within this Realme. And therefore I doe vtterly renounce, &amp; forſake all forrain iuriſdictions, powers, ſuperiorities, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, and doe promiſe that from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, I will beare faith and true allegiance to the Kings highnes, his heires, and lawful ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, and to my power ſhall defend all iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, priviledges, preheminences, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities granted, or belonging to the Kings highneſſe, his heires and ſucceſſors, or vnited, or annexed to the imperiall crowne of this Realme. So God me helpe, and by the contents of this booke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides the ſetting downe of this oath, thus in theſe tearmes, of which the Papiſts are afraid, as of ſome monſter, I muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the meaning and intendment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; what is challenged thereby, and what is vnſought for by his Maieſtie, and from whom more ſooner, and trulier may wee learne the ſcope and drift thereof, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from him to whom we owe it, and to whome of right it belongeth to be ſworne. His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie therefore having proved, from many and ſundry ſentences, titles, and preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6746:6"/>both in the old Teſtament, and in the new, that Chriſtian Princes within their dominions, haue warrant to governe the Church, as well as the reſt of their people in being
<hi>Cuſtodes vtriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tabulae,</hi> perſons to whom God hath commended and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the keeping of both tables, doth there diſclaime and denie <hi>that hee hath any power to make new articles of faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">What the king doth either take or refuſe by the oath of ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy. His Maieſties Apol pag. <hi>108.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>(that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice he leaveth to the Pope) or to ſet vp anie points of religion not warranted by the word of God: but by commanding obedience to bee given to the word of God, by reforming the religion according to his preſcribed will, by aſſiſting the spirituall power with the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſword, by reforming of corruptions, by pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>curing due obedience to the Church; by iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and cutting of all frivolous queſtions and ſchiſmes, as Conſtantine did. And finally by making decorum to bee obſerved in every thing, and eſtabliſhing orders to bee obſerved in all indifferent things for that purpoſe.</hi> And this is the only intent of this oath of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy.</p>
            <p>This is inlarged with more words,<note place="margin">Rain. conf. with Hart. c. <hi>10.</hi> div.
<hi>1.</hi>
               </note> but to the ſame effect, by D. Rainolds in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with M. Hart. For the king (ſaith he) to be ſupreame governour of all his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions in things ſpirituall and temporall,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6746:6"/>is to haue the preheminence over all rulers in government of matters touching God and man within his dominions, and this by the Scripture is Ceſars right. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. The high Prieſt is ordained for me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thoſe things that appertaine to God to do them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Prieſt duty</hi> Heb. 5.1.</note> that is, to offer gifts and ſacrifices for ſin; this is the peculiar duty of the prieſt, which if the Prince meddle with as
<hi>Ozias</hi> did,<note place="margin">2. Chro. 26. v. 16, 18.19.</note> who would haue burnt incenſe vpon the Altar of incenſe, a thing inioined to Prieſts only, then hee tranſgreſſeth the bounds of his office, and provoketh vengeance of the Lord vpon him<note place="margin">The Princes du tie.</note> But to provide by Civill puniſhments, and orders, that Prieſtes doe their dutie in things concerning God; not only Prieſts, but people too, it is the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces charge, and ſo hee is ordained to deale in things of God<note place="margin">Iudges, 27
5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6</note> For when Michah had an Idols chappell in his houſe, with a veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Images, in thoſe daies (ſaith the text) there was no king in Iſraell, but every man did that which was good in his own eies<note place="margin">Iudges. 18.1.2</note> And againe there was no king in Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell when the men of <hi>Dan</hi> got that Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous ſtuffe with an Idololatrous Prieſt,<note place="margin">17.</note> &amp; went a whoring after it, which being ſaid in like ſort, when adultery was committed,<note place="margin">19.</note> and with adultery murther, doth ſhew, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6746:7"/>as the ſubiect ſhould haue beene reſtrained from murther and adulterie,<note place="margin">Iudg. 19.1.2 25.26.</note> ſo from Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try too, by the Princes ſword, ſith all theſe ſinnes raigned,<note place="margin">Iud. 20.28. Deut. 17.19.</note> not for want of a Prieſt, but of a king in Iſraell. And where the king is willed by Moſes, to keepe all the words of the law to doe them, the Lord meant ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that he ought to keepe them, not only as a private man, but as a king, by ſeeking and providing that all his ſubiects did their duties both to God and man. Wherefore ſince the ſupremacie we giue to our Prince in things Eccleſiaſticall,<note place="margin">2. Chr. 29. v. 5. 21: 27.30. 2. Chr.
30.1.6.12.</note> to deale therein as <hi>Ezechias</hi> did, firſt to command that the Prieſts and Levites doe doe their duties, &amp; afterward the people to come and ſerue the Lord, and finally both Prieſt and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to reforme themſelues for maintenance of religion; not as
<hi>Ozias</hi> who (as is ſaid before) would burne incenſe: nor ours to preach the word, miniſter the ſacraments, celebrate the prayers, or practiſe diſcipline of the Church, but to provide, that thoſe things bee done as they ought, by them whom God hath called therevnto. And this is to Giue Caeſar, no more then is Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars; for every lawful Prince is the ſupream governour of his owne ſubiects in things ſpirituall and temporall. And the Parlame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6746:7"/>may take an oath of Engliſh men for <hi>Iames</hi> our King, againſt the Pope,<note place="margin">A preſident for the lawfulneſſe of the oath of ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>premacie. <hi>2 Kings. 11.4.17.</hi>
               </note> againſt <hi>Athalia</hi> that vſurped his ſtate.</p>
            <p>Now in this maner, as hath been expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and no otherwiſe, doth his Maieſtie take, or we giue him the title of <hi>Supreame governour in matters spirituall and Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall,</hi> which ſo vnderſtood would cut of a great number of addle &amp; idle talk which at this day paſſeth amongſt them touching it, who know not what they ſay<note place="margin">To governe and rule the Church of God is of two ſorts. The kings duty conſiſteth in this <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> For to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh the offices which are by God at this day ſet to rule and govern his Church, muſt we not needs ſay they are of 2 kindes and ſorts? The one being by the ſupreame authority, and power of the ſword, to guid care for, provide, direct, and aide Gods Church, to further, maintaine, and ſet forth the true religion, vnitie, and quietneſſe of Gods Church, and to overſee, viſit, reform, reſtraine, amend, and correct all manner of perſons, with al maner errors, ſuperſtitions hereſies, ſchiſmes, abuſes, offences, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, and enormities, in or about Gods Church, which government, and rule, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to kings, queenes, and princes, and not to Apoſtles, Biſhops, and Prieſts. The
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6746:8"/>other is to governe &amp; rule by feeding the flocke of Chriſt with the ſpiritual food of Gods word,<note place="margin">The Prieſts du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty conſiſteth in this.</note> preaching it in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon,<note place="margin">2.</note> adminiſtration of the ſacraments and power of the keyes, which is the onely rule and government belonging to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, Biſhops, and Miniſters of Chriſts Church.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Examples of the god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y kings of Iſraell, &amp; their practiſe.</note>Shall we ſee then by the practiſe of the Godly kings in the time of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>this ſupreame government,</hi> I meane in ſpirituall and Eccleſiaſticall matters, and over the perſons exerciſing the ſame, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed?<note place="margin">Tortura Torti, pag. <hi>363.</hi>
               </note> From thence we muſt begin, from the common wealth of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> all this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion hath its ſtrength and force<note place="margin">Eccleſia eſt in republica, ſed reſpubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca non eſt in Eccleſia.</note> For, in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell the people of God, did God ordaine the kingdome, and the Church in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome according to his owne mind, &amp; ſince we haue no example in the new Teſtament, we muſt take it from the old. The Empire and the Church in that time were never u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited in one; the Empire was then enimie to the Church; therefore what charge the kings had of religion muſt be fetched from thence; where the civill policie, and the Church are as it were twins, and friendly imbrace together, not where they are ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated; From that fountaine therefore of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6746:8"/>
               <hi>Iſraell,</hi> doe we deriue our cauſe, and from that example (where both are together, where the Church is in the kingdome) doe we informe our ſelues of the Government, both of our Church and Kingdome. Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching their practiſe therefore, I doubt not, but to make our queſtion cleere, inſomuch that I hope I ſhall finde none ſo ſhameleſſe as to deny
<hi>the principall care in the matter of religion belonged to the king,</hi> which is ſeene by this one argument drawne from the whole courſe of the holy hiſtorie<note place="margin">Note this eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially.</note> 
               <hi>That looke how the king was changed,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> 1.</note>
               <hi>ſo was the forme of religion:</hi>
               <note place="margin"> 2.</note> 
               <hi>and that change was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies aſcribed to the king as his deed: neither could the Prieſts at any time ſo order the mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter that any change was made,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> 3.</note> 
               <hi>from the worſe to the better; or from the better to the worſe, But if the chieftie had beene theires,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> 4.</note> 
               <hi>ſome one Prieſt or other, would haue beene found at one time or other, or at the leaſt ſome part of the people, though the king had beene otherwiſe affected, that would haue kept the worſhip of God ſound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will now beginne with the example of Iehoſhaphat mentioned in the text of the Apology,<note place="margin">Tortura Torti, pag<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>364.</hi> Iehoſhaphat the king.</note> whoſe doings in the matter of re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligion is notably ſet downe in the chapter quoted<note place="margin">2, Chron. c. 19 v. 4.</note> 
               <hi>The king went through the people
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6746:9"/>from Berſheba to mount Ephraim, &amp; brought them againe vnto the Lord God of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> He brought them again to the Lord, that is, he cauſed that they were a Church, and hee did it by his kingly authoritie, whereby alſo afterward in the 8. verſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>V.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>hee appointed Iudges in Iſraell,</hi> of the Levites, Prieſts, and chiefe of the families of Iſrael, to iudge the cauſe of the Lord which is ſaid in the 10. v. to be of the law, and of ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies; And what greater ſupremacie can there be, then of ſetting and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Iudges</hi> in matters of religion? And where the text ſaith, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>V.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>Amariah the Prieſt ſhall be the chiefe over you, in all matters of the Lord; and Zebadiah the ſon of Iſhmaell, a ruler of the houſe of Iuda, ſhall be for all the kings affaires, and the Levites ſhall be officers before you;</hi> it appeareth plainely that the king Iehoſhaphat commandeth the Prieſt to be chiefe in thoſe things which belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the Lord; and gaue the captaine, or Lieutena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t charge of thoſe things which appertaineth to the Common weale: <note place="margin">Iehoſhaphat ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed both. The ground of the high com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land taken from Ezra, cap. <hi>7.</hi> v. <hi>25
26.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> By which deed of his he teacheth vs, that no leſſe the one, then the other, doth princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally belong vnto the kings charge, ſince firſt he could reduce the people to the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and when they were reduced,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6746:9"/>to appoint Iudges, and by his kingly pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to divide the cauſes amongſt the Iudges, &amp; who ſhould be chiefe, &amp; in what things. Thus hath the civill policie and the church diſtinct cauſes, and diſtinct courts; but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the king, no leſſe the church then the common wealth hath them, by whoſe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and command Iudges do ſit, &amp;
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mariah</hi> over the one and <hi>Zabadias</hi> over the other. Both of them handle matters belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to their courts, but both of them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the king.</p>
            <p>What <hi>Ioſias</hi> did in the affaires of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appeareth by that which is written of him. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tortura torti, pag.</hi> 367. <hi>Ioſias.</hi> 2. Chron 22.11.</note>
               <hi>He made the booke of the law, which was new lie found to be read vnto the people.</hi> The text ſaith further, the king called the aſſembly togither, commanded the book to be read vnto them, being read entered into a newe covenant with the Lord, <note place="margin">An
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> &amp; tooke an oath of the people for the performance thereof. There the king commanded the high prieſt himſelfe, &amp; the reſt of the prieſts of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond order, that they ſhould caſt out of the temple of the Lord, &amp; burne all the veſſe is that belonged to <hi>Baall,</hi> and throw downe their high places. He alſo gaue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the keeping of the
<hi>Paſſeouer</hi> a new, and at a word, for the whole reformantion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6746:10"/>of religion. Here is as much for the <hi>Kings Supremacie,</hi> as either we giue, or his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie requireth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ioſua. Read the whole ſtory in the book of Ioſua.</note>The hiſtorie of <hi>Ioſua</hi> before theſe, is plaine enough for this, who although hee were none other but a <hi>Civill Magiſtrate,</hi> yet aſſoone as he was choſen of God, &amp; ſet as a ruler over the people, he received com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandements aſpecially touching <hi>Religion,</hi> and the ſervice of God. He cauſed the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be circumciſed. He cauſed Altars for their bloudy ſacrifices to be erected. Hee cauſed the people to make their ſacrifices. He commanded the Prieſts to take vp the Arke. Hee cauſed the <hi>Deuteronomie</hi> to bee written in ſtones. He cauſed both the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and the curſings of the Lord to bee pronounced. He ſpake openly to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and fraid them from Idolatry. All theſe were caſes of <hi>Religion,</hi> and not of <hi>Civill po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The doings of <hi>Ezechias</hi> &amp; <hi>Aſa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezechias. Aſa.</hi> 2. Chron. 29. &amp; 15. 1. King. 15.8. 1. King. 2.27. <hi>Tortura Torti.</hi>
371.</note> in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the temple when it was defiled; King <hi>Salomons</hi> depoſing of the high Prieſt <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>athar,</hi> and placing <hi>Zadoc</hi> in his roome, are frequently knowne. I need not much ſtand on them. Wherefore did <hi>Salomon</hi> thruſt out <hi>Abiathar,</hi> but becauſe he was guilty of treaſon againſt the king? Marke the words
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6746:10"/>
               <hi>Go to Anathoth vnto thine owne fields, keepe thy ſelfe there, thou art a man of death, or art worthy of death, but I will not this day kill thee.</hi> Theſe are the words of a king in his ſupreame government, over an high prieſt. To confine men within a circuit; where they are worthy of death to giue them life, to change a capitall penaltie into an eaſier of depoſing, is the authority alſo of a king. Moreover, by the ſame authority, that hee placed
<hi>Banaiah</hi> in <hi>Ioabs</hi> ſtead over his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, (which no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I thinke wil denie to be done by his kingly ſupremacie) by the ſame, and none other did he place <hi>Sadoc</hi> in ſtead of <hi>Abiathar</hi> over the prieſthood; ſo it is in the 35. verſe. <hi>And the king put Benaiah the ſonne of Iehoida in Ioabs roome over the hoſt: and the king ſet Sadoc the Prieſt in the roome of Abiathar.</hi> Done by the kings au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority both, both in one &amp; the ſame verſe.</p>
            <p>But that I may at once diſpatch out of the old teſtament, <note place="margin">Tortura Torti, pag. <hi>380.</hi>
               </note> this whole queſtion of the kings ſupremacie, and that the right of it, may be more fully ſeene (although e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough is ſaid before) &amp; what is vnderſtood thereby, ſo to ſtop if it be poſſible their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſlanders riſing vpon it, deviſed only by themſelues: In few this it is.</p>
            <p>Firſt vnder the title of ſupremacie the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6746:11"/>king bringeth in no new Popedome into the church, for hee ſetteth not vp a power like <hi>Aaron</hi> the high prieſt of making a <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Calfe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 32. v. 4. 1. King. 12 28. <hi>Theſe things the king taketh not.</hi>
               </note> or of propoſing it to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped as <hi>Ieroboam</hi> the king did his; or maketh new articles of faith or ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mereth any new formes of religion in the ſervice of God. Neither burneth he incenſe with <hi>Ozias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Chro 26.16 2. Sam. 6.6.</note> or of touching the Arke with <hi>Oza.</hi> Nor ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth he the office of teaching; we place the primacie in
<hi>Governing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The king is the chiefe Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; but not the chiefeſt doctor.</note> &amp; not in <hi>teaching.</hi> And therefore we ſay he is the <hi>Chiefe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour,</hi> but not the chiefe <hi>teacher,</hi> or <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor.</hi> He expoundeth not the hard doubtes of the law, nor preacheth the word, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtreth the holy things, or vſeth impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hands; or exerciſeth the keyes, or laieth any eccleſiaſticall cenſure on anie. At a word hee taketh nothing to him that belongeth <hi>ad Sacerdotale munus</hi> to the prieſtly function, or is annexed to the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of order. If they vnderſtand vs otherwiſe they detract but will not vnderſtand.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Theſe things the king taketh.</note>But in the matter of outward governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to command, that he challengeth to himſelfe, and we very willingly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it. The care of religion belongeth to the kingly office, &amp; not only to the prieſts; And in kings it is the chiefeſt, which they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6746:11"/>are not only bounde to challenge as their owne, in keeping it from externall force a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; but at home from the negligence of men, and when it is decaied, it is their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to ſee it repaired. For when by, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry law of God, <note place="margin">Deut. 17.18. Ioſhua.
1.8.</note> the king is <hi>keeper</hi> and <hi>defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> not of the ſecond table only, but of the firſt too; his Maieſtie doubteth not, but that the care of the firſt table, doth belong vnto him, and maketh the due regard there of his firſt ſtudy. And ſince every ſoule is ſaid to bee ſubiect vnto him, he will haue care of the ſoules of his ſubiects, more and before the care of their bodies. And parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly whatſoever in the matter of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the kings of Iſrael did, and did not without praiſe, the king hath power and right to do the ſame.</p>
            <p>Power to make lawes by his kingly au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tortura Torti, pag.</hi>
381. <hi>Power to make lawes.</hi> Dan. 3.29. Ion 3 7. Eſter. 9 26. 1. Macc. 4 56.59.</note> that God bee not blaſphemed; (none I hope wil deny it, the king of Babel did it.) To pacifie God by faſting, ſo did the king of Ninive. To honour him by kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſolemne feaſts, ſo did
<hi>Heſter</hi> with the feaſt of <hi>Purim;</hi> And as <hi>Iudas Machabeus,</hi> when he proclaimed the feaſt of Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. Finally he hath ſupremacie in all thoſe things, touching which, <note place="margin">In codice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in Authenticis in capitulari bus.</note> lawes were made in the <hi>Code,</hi> in <hi>the Authentickes,</hi> &amp; the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6746:12"/>by <hi>Conſtantine, Theodoſius, Iuſtinian,</hi> and <hi>Charles the great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then he hath power of appointing thoſe that ſhall determine buſineſſe according to the law ſo made, as <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> did. Then he hath power of binding his ſubiects by an oath, <note place="margin">2. Chr. 15.14. &amp;c. 34. v. 32.</note> that they violate not the law ſo made, as <hi>Aſa,</hi> and <hi>Ioſias</hi> did. And whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall offend againſt the lawe ſo made, although he pretend the worſhip of God, <note place="margin">Deut. 13.10. &amp;
15. Levit. 24.23. Num. 15.35.</note> as whether he be a falſe Prophet, or an Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lolater, or blaſphemer, or breaker of the Saboth; in every, and all theſe caſes, the king is to puniſh him by his kingly autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
            <p>Power alſo he hath of <hi>calling the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude together,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Chr.
13.3.</note> by his owne authoritie; of bringing backe the Arke, and ſetting it in its owne place, <note place="margin">2. Chr. 19 4.</note> as did <hi>David.</hi> And of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the people backe to the worſhippe of God, as did <hi>Iehoſhaphat.</hi> Of dedicating the temple as did
<hi>Salomon;</hi> and renuing the houſe of the Lord, <note place="margin">1. Kings, 8 64. 2. Chr.
24 4. &amp; 29.5.</note> as <hi>Ioas</hi> did; And of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging it, when it was pollutted, as
<hi>Ezechias did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And albeit the king doe not thinke, that it was for naught, that God charged him <hi>To write out a copy of the law for himſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 17.19.</note> 
               <hi>that hee might continually haue it with him,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6746:12"/>read it diligently, and meditate therein daie and night,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſua. 1.8.</note> and from it to learne the worſhip of God, even to the ceremonies themſelues; neither that it was ſaid ſo to him, in reſpect that he ſhould reſt altogether, vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans report, iudging nothing of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: yet in theſe things he ſhall ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Eleazar</hi> the Prieſt, and willingly aske counſell of him; and ſhall require the law of them whoſe lipps preſerue knowledge. He ſhall call thoſe to the making of lawes for the Church, whom it is meet ſhould bee called, and thoſe whome reaſon doth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, are the moſt skilfull, and that can in thoſe things giue counſell beſt. And then, in thoſe things which appertaine to God, command <hi>Amarias</hi> the Prieſt,
<note place="margin">2. Chr. 19.11.</note> and not <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>badias</hi> the Captaine to be chiefe.</p>
            <p>Touching the perſon, <note place="margin">Touching the perſons. Tortura Torti. pag.
<hi>381.338.</hi> &amp; <hi>376. 1. Sam. 15.17.</hi>
               </note> it is likewiſe as cleere <hi>that the king hath ſupremacy over them.</hi> A power of adminiſtring lawes to all men, of all degrees, and to ſpeak in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the holy ſcripture, <hi>head of the tribe of Levi,</hi> no leſſe then of the reſt of the <hi>tribes</hi> nor no leſſe head of the clergie, then of the laitie. So the Prophet ſpeaketh to the king. <hi>When thou waſt little in thine own ſight,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Saul the king, head of the tribes.</note> 
               <hi>waſt thou not made the head of the tribes of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell?</hi> Now amongſt the tribes of Iſraell, was
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6746:13"/>the tribe of Levi, therefore the king is head of the Leviticall tribe, in which
<hi>Tribe</hi> was <hi>Ahimelech</hi> the Prieſt, vnder the king his head. This is farther expreſſed by the name of <hi>Father</hi> and mother, and who head but they, <note place="margin">Iudg. 5.7.</note> over whom they are ſet? <hi>Debora,</hi> a woman, is called a mother in Iſraell. <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias,</hi> father; (and heare you papiſt) of the Prieſts, ſo he ſpeaketh vnto them. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.11. <hi>Now my ſonnes be not negligent.</hi> A father then was <hi>Ezechias,</hi> and a father o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Prieſts. Looke then what honour and
<hi>ſupremacy</hi> Princes haue, they haue it by no other commandement then the <hi>Fift,</hi> of honouring our father, &amp; them for their fatherly care of the Church, as of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; And if any ſhall deale preſumptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt <hi>Abiathar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut.
17.12.</note> the king hath power by his lawes to puniſh him; even to the putting out of
<hi>Abiathar</hi> himſelfe from his Prieſthood, <note place="margin">1. Kings. 2 27. <hi>Touching the things.</hi>
               </note> if he deſerue it.</p>
            <p>Touching the things erected, or vſed to falſe worſhip, power hee hath of pulling downe the high places, that is, to aboliſh ſtrange worſhip; not only over the <hi>Golden Calfe</hi> which <hi>Aaron</hi> made, as <hi>Moſes</hi> had in breaking it to peeces: <note place="margin">Exod. 32.20.</note> but over the braſen ſerpent erected by <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. King. 18 v 4</note> as had
<hi>Ezechias,</hi> when the <hi>Golden Calfe</hi> is abuſed to Idolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6746:13"/>or the braſen ſerpent to ſuperſtition, of deſtroying them both.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In things indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent.</note>And for the things, which belong to the
<hi>Beauty</hi> of Gods Church, which bee called <hi>indifferent,</hi> he hath power alſo to order the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as <hi>Ioas</hi> did. <note place="margin">2. Ch. 24. v. 12</note> And when occaſion of ſchiſmes and diviſions, by trifling and fooliſh que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions is miniſtred, by his authoritie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine them, as <hi>Conſtantine</hi> did. And this I hope no man will deny to be his right. <note place="margin">Socrat. Eccleſ. hiſi. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, if the Romiſh Catholike had rather haue examples from Chriſtians, then from the common wealth of the Iewes; let him knowe that <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom.
2. ad po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pul. Antioch.</hi> Theodoſius cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led head of all men by Chryſoſt.</note> a famous pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late in his time, called <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour by this name <hi>head,</hi> and not only the head, but that which in the head is moſt high, <hi>the top of the head, and that of all men in the earth.</hi> And I make no queſtion, but that there was a man the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on the earth who was the Biſhop of Rome. If we craue more examples, I dare truely ſay the Catholike Church was ſo far from diſtaſting this <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy in Princes,</hi> that it called and inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, the Emperours <hi>Charles</hi> the great, &amp; <hi>Lodowike, Rectores religionis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tortura</hi> 7 <hi>pag.</hi> 379.</note> 
               <hi>Guiders of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> in the publike acts of their Councell. And yet againe, if nothing will ſerue the turne but the very word
<hi>Governour,</hi> lette
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6746:14"/>them that doubt of it, read it in the eight generall Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell (ſo called by them) where the Emperour <hi>Baſilius</hi> is ſtiled <hi>Govern our of the vniverſall Church.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gubernator univerſalis navis eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticae.</note> And
<hi>Conſtantine</hi> himſelfe doubted not to ſay of himſelfe <hi>that he was a Biſhop without, as others were within the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe duties touching the Church, and titles to Princes belonging, are thoſe very things, which we ſay appertaine vnto the kings <hi>Supremacie,</hi> by the law of God. The Kings and princes of the world now are in no worſe caſe, then were the kinges in the old Teſtament. They are vnder the ſame condition, and therefore the ſame <hi>primacy</hi> is due vnto them, and the ſame ought to be yeelded vnto them. And therefore I may iuſtly conclude here with that ſaying of <hi>Scaliger to Lypſius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Scaliger tu Lyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius.</note>
               <hi>Nos non ſumus novato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, ſed vos veteratores eſtis.</hi> Wee are no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novators, but they that deny this truth are falſe deceivers. What other exceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s they take, of his Maieſties vſurping part of the Prieſts office in the worſhip of God, is a monſter of their owne begetting, againſt which they may fight, as with their ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, but ſhall never ſtrike vs. The reader that is not wilfully blind, will herein ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit his iudgement vnto the truth.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:6746:14"/>
            <p>Thus I haue ſhewed by the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <note place="margin">That the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperours practiſed this ſupremacy in matters of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note> by the practiſe of the kings there, my intended purpoſe: It ſhall not bee amiſſe now to ſee how the godly Emperours in the primitiue Church of Chriſt, dealt in the buſines of religion, according to that
<hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy</hi> we ſpeake of; a great part of which <hi>was their calling of generall Concells,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calling of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees. 1. Councell of Nice. Socrat. l. <hi>1.</hi> c <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by as by a ſpeedy way to ridde the Church from the infection of peſtilent hereſies. The Biſhops of the firſt councell of
<hi>Nice</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe in their <hi>Synodicall Epiſtle,</hi> that they were called by the authoritie of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour; <hi>The Synod met together (ſay they) when Conſtantine the moſt beloved of God gathered vs, out of diverſe cities and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</hi>
               <note place="margin">By the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine. Tortura Torti, pag <hi>165. Et ſynodi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creta confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, conſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>navit. 2</hi> Of Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople.</note> They ſubmitted themſelues vnto him ſo the words goe; <hi>And confirming the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the Synod, he ſigned them.</hi> The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d generall councell held at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> was called by the authoritie of
<hi>Theodoſius</hi> the elder, <hi>wee met together according to the letters of your Maieſtie.</hi> And againe, <hi>your Maieſtie hath honoured the Church, by your letters of calling vs hither.</hi> In their Epiſtle to him; <hi>What ſoever hath bin neceſſarily done in the holy Synode, we refer them to your God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe. We deſire alſo that the ſentence of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6746:15"/>Synode may bee confirmed by your Maieſties writing. And as you did honour vs when you called vs hither by your letters: ſo wee deſire that of thoſe things which are decreed, you would by ſigning them, put an end to all things</hi> The third is the Councell of
<hi>Epheſus</hi> called likewiſe by the Emperours authority, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Of Epheſus.</note> 
               <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoſius</hi> the younger, &amp; <hi>Valentinian,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is ſo plaine evidence, as in none more plainer. For the Councell it ſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth ſeaven times in ſeaven Epiſtles, that they came together <hi>by the appointment of their authorities.</hi> And often times they ſay, <hi>by their ſentence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Secundumo raculum man datum reſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptum.</note> 
               <hi>commandement &amp; letters.</hi> In this Epiſtle they ſay, <hi>wherevpon we all fly to the authoritie of your highneſſe, be ſeeching the ſame, that thoſe things which are enacted againſt Neſtorius, and thoſe that are gon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray with him, may haue their force and ſtrength; And that thoſe things whereof Neſtorius is autor may be void and diſanul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</hi> The councell of
<hi>Chalcedon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. <hi>Chalcedon.</hi>
               </note> being the laſt of the firſt foure, witneſſeth as much; <hi>The Synod was aſſembled by the decree of the moſt Godly and faith full Emperours, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinian and Martian.</hi> In their Epiſtle this; <hi>The holy and great councell was called toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by the grace of God and decrees of your highneſſe.</hi> The ſame words are expreſſed by
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6746:15"/>them when they relate what was done in the councell. And of them, that is,
<note place="margin">Et ab illis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> miſſione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perunt ut &amp; Epheſini.</note> of the Emperours, the Councell craue leaue to depart, as thoſe of <hi>Epheſus</hi> did. And Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſaith, <hi>We confirme the reverend Synod by the ſacred decree of our highneſſe..</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This truth is ſo ſtrong, <note place="margin">De conc. &amp; eccl. l. 1. c. 13.</note> that
<hi>Bellarmine</hi> although he purpoſely intended the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of it, yet doth he plainly confeſſe it. He addeth 4 reaſons to ſhew, why the firſt fower Generall councels (whereof I ſpake before) were called by the Emperours, but he addeth to dawbe vp the matter,
<note place="margin">A Gloſſe beſides the text. Our queſtion is by whoſe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and not by whoſe conſent councels were called.</note> 
               <hi>It was with the conſent and minde of the Pope:</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our queſtion here is, by <hi>whoſe authority, &amp; not by whoſe conſent,</hi> they were called. As if the queſtion were, <hi>by whoſe authority is war proclaimed? Bellarmine</hi> ſhould ſay. It is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede by the Princes authority, but not without the conſent of the nobles &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons: therefore authority of proclaiming warre belongeth not to the Prince. Beſides the Emperours required the conſent of the other Patriarches, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>4</hi> Reaſons of Bellarmine, to proue that the Emperours cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the firſt <hi>4.</hi> generall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells.</note> aſwell as of the Biſhop of Rome, but the <hi>Supreame right &amp; autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie remaineth in them.</hi> But to leaue
<hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> in his poore excuſe, &amp; to come to his 4. reaſons, thus they ſtand.
1. Becauſe at that time the ancient law imperiall was in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6746:16"/>force which did forbidde al aſſemblies and companies of men, without the Emperours authority, becauſe the Emperours feared ſeditions and tumults might haue ariſen. 2, If that law had not beene in force, yet ſee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing the Emperours governed the world in great peace, a councell could not bee held, but in ſome imperiall citty, and no reaſon it is, that an aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly ſhould be made to one citty out of the whole world, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the licence of the Lord of that place; <note place="margin">From hence it appeareth that the Pope had not all temporal Lordſhip<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and rule, as now they claime for him.</note> as now at this day, if a councel be held out of the territories of the Pope, as in <hi>France, Spaine,</hi> or
<hi>Germanie,</hi> without doubt his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent muſt be asked, in whoſe citty or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince it is. 3. Becauſe in thoſe times gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall councels were made by the publike charges; eſpecially touching the bringing of the Biſhops to the place where the coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell was. For they were carried on horſes, or in citty wagons, without charge of the churches. And touching that of
<hi>Nice,</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of the councell al the biſhops lived at the charge of the Emperour. This appeareth alſo out of <hi>Theodoret;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. hiſt.
<hi>2.16.</hi>
               </note> where, in the conference betweene <hi>Liberius</hi> the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome, and <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, <hi>Liberius</hi> for the equity of his cauſe prayed that a generall councell be ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6746:16"/>anſwere was made, the publike reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues woulde not ſerue for the bringing of the Biſhops. 4. Becauſe, although at that time the Pope was head over all, even Emperours in ſpirituall things, yet in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall matters, <note place="margin">The Pope could doe nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours mind.</note> hee did ſubiect himſelfe to the Emperours, and therefore he could doe nothing without the Emperours goodwil. And when he might haue only prayed aide of the Emperour for the calling of a <hi>Synod,</hi> yet becauſe hee acknowledged the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour his
<hi>Temporall Lord,</hi> he did <hi>beſeech him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The pope beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</note> that he would command a <hi>Synod</hi> to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. But after thoſe times all thoſe cauſes were changed. <note place="margin">Factum alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius alij noce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re non debet;
<hi>and therefore aske</hi> quo iure.</note> For that imperiall lawe firſt ſpoken of, doth not now ſtand in force, and the Pope who is head in ſpirituall matters, is not now ſubiect to the Emperour in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall. Thus far Bellarmine. But <hi>O tempora, o mores!</hi> O vnequall times that ſo many things ſhould be then lawfull, whereof not one of them ſhall bee now lawfull? Then the Pope intreated the Emperour, now the Pope commandes him, or at leaſt not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats him. Then the Pope was ſubiect to the Emperour in temporall things, now he is not ſo, that is to ſay the Emperour is now no Emperour, nor the Pope no Pope. But in former times <hi>(tempora mutantur)</hi> The
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6746:17"/>Emperour was Emperour indeed, &amp; Pope, Pope indeede, that is, hee was obedient to the Emperour, as he ought. Then the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Empire ſtood firme &amp; vpright; nowe (ſaith <hi>Bellarmine</hi>) <hi>Romanum imperium iam ferè deletum eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De nom. Pon. l. 2. c. 2 § prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicit.</note> the Romane Empire is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt extinct. A pleaſant time for Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I proved, ſufficiently I truſt that the firſt fowre general Councels were called by the Emperours <hi>authority,</hi> &amp; that they were <hi>confirmed</hi> by them; not one of them by the Pope, nor any of them in <hi>Italy,</hi> all without his command, in places far re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from him in <hi>Greece</hi> where the world knoweth he was little reſpected.</p>
            <p>Other confirmation of this truth there is out of the Eccleſiaſticall hiſtories of
<hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> in the life of <hi>Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tine;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſticall hiſtories omitted in this.</note> 
               <hi>Socrates, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zomene, Theodoret,</hi> and <hi>Evagrius,</hi> al which do deliver a perfect ſummme of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches infancie, groth, and perfecteſt eſtate, for the ſpace of 600 yeeres after Chriſt; and in moſt ample maner ſhew, that that ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie in <hi>Eccleſiaſticall matters</hi> which wee now ſeek for, was then reſiant in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperours, and not in the Pope. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall councels there are alſo ſomewhat be yond the time ſpoken of, in the raigne of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6746:17"/>
               <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>great,</hi> which might bee here brought in, but at this time I will leaue the proſequutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of any of thoſe authorities of purpoſe, becauſe I haſten to an author of great credit with our adverſaries, which is <hi>Leo the biſhop of Rome,</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned before, in whom I deſire the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but to ſee what he gaue to the Emperours in his time, &amp; how fitly his teſtimonie fitteth our purpoſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of them but this, that if they find, that he gaue the Emperours as much as we giue his Maieſtie, and that we giue his Maieſtie no more than he giveth them, they woulde hence forth ſurceaſe, to refuſe that which is iuſt, or if it be vniuſt to condemne thoſe pious and godly Emperours, of intruſion vpon the Popes right, as they doe his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie.</p>
            <p>For the tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlation of the Epiſtles, I muſt craue pardon, of any curious eie that ſhall compare them with the originals, if they find my barren Engliſh ſhort in expreſſing the elegancie of <hi>Leos</hi> latine ſtile; <note place="margin">Leo epiſt. 83. ad Paleſtinos Monachos. Non valentes in Graecum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquiurn aptè &amp; propriè La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, &amp;c.</note> ſince in things of this nature, as an vnskilfull inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter, I am not able (as he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaineth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of ſome other) to put the Latin phraſe aptly and kindly into our Engliſh tongue, ſeeing in expreſſing hard &amp; difficult things al men cannot do it in their own language,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6746:18"/>much leſſe in another. But I haue done all, that I haue done of a willing minde to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their iudgement, who haue not ſo much as to vnderſtand the Latine. I knowe the learned knowe them better then my ſelfe. The meaning of my author, I truſt ſhal not bee inverted; <note place="margin">Aucupium ſyllabarum. <hi>Tortura Torti, fol.</hi> 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>9. Melius eſt ut Grammatici nos reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quam populi non intelligant.</note> if any man ſhall hunt after ſyllables, in ſo waightie a cauſe, hee ſhall with the wiſe bee held guilty of raiſing a quarrell without iuſt cauſe. For who doth not know that to every tongue, there is its owne proper phraſe and maner of ſpeech, and that that which is written in one, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee ſo rendred againe in another, that at leaſt there ſhall bee no difference, in anie little ſentence, but that one word muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer another wholy and throughout? So the intent be kept, it is meere folly to lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh about words; <note place="margin">Vniuſt taxing. In his returne of vntruthes. <hi>4.</hi> art.
<hi>117.</hi> b. fol. <hi>Inſtigante di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abolo.</hi>
               </note> an vpright and right meaning heart, in theſe caſes ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt that petty kind of reprehenſion vſed by D. Stapleton againſt B. Iuell for his tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Inſtigante diabolo, they were altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inflamed and led by the divell.</hi> And thus Stapleton crieth out; Lo the ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cred words of M. Iuels tender hart <hi>inſtigante diabolo,</hi> is ſaith he, <hi>the divell pricking them and moving them forward.</hi> Now I appeale to any man, but to him that hath indeed a cancred hart
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6746:18"/>to tell mee what difference in ſubſtance there is betweene theſe two,
<hi>altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed and led by the divell:</hi> And, <hi>the divell pricking and moving them forward.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stap. ib. <hi>4</hi> art. <hi>131.</hi> a. fol. Contrary to the minds of the moſt part of the Biſhops.</note> And where the Biſhop ſaith, <hi>that the Imperour Gratian made Nectarius Biſhop of Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople contrary to the minds of the moſt part of the Biſhops:</hi> here M. Iuell overreacheth his author (ſaith Stapleton) for
<hi>Sozomene</hi> ſaith, <hi>many of the Biſhops gaine ſaying it.</hi> A ſtrong cavill I wiſſe, and a maine difference there is no doubt betweene <hi>contrary to the minds of moſt:</hi> And, <hi>many gaine ſaying it.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſince
<hi>Chriſtophorſon</hi> (who both for advantage, and skill for the Church of Romes cauſe, was as ſtrong as Stapleton) tranſlateth the Greeke, <hi>multis ſacerdotibus reluctantibus, many Biſhops, or Prieſts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, ſtriving, ſtrugling, or wraſtling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</hi> And what is this, <hi>but contrarie to their minds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither would I haue any ſober minded man, cavill at ſuch alleaged ſentences as this. Where B. Iuell alleageth <hi>Liberatus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Liberatus allea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged by B. Iuell. Brevia, cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> &amp; alleageth him thus, <hi>Liberatus ſaith that Leo the Biſhop of Rome, with other moe Biſhops of Italy, fell on their knees and deſired the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Valentinian, and the Empreſſe Eudo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xia, to appoint a Councell, and yet could not
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6746:19"/>obtaine it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Staplet ut an te pag. 142,</note> In this allegation out of <hi>Libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> two vntruthes are (ſaith Stapleton) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by M. Iuel. For neither <hi>Leo</hi> the Pope fell on his knees to the Emperour Valenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian, neither did they deſire him to appoint a Councell, but to write to <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperour of the Eaſt about it. Nowe the firſt vntruth, as Stapleton imagineth is, that <hi>Leo</hi> fell not on his knees, as did the reſt; but that he intreated only, and other Biſhops fell on their knees. The ſecond, That Leo beſought not <hi>Valentinian</hi> for a Councell, (as B. Iuell ſaith) But beſought <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an and Eudoxia his wife, that they woulde write to Theodoſius about it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Biſhops of Italy and the Pope, deſire the Emperour to call a Councell.</note> A marvellous thing it is to ſee what a wit wickednes hath For what is it to the ſubſtance of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whether <hi>Leo</hi> prayed a Councell of
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinian,</hi> or prayed him to write to <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> that a Councell might be called. To an Emperour hee wrote. It is the more ſigne that <hi>Leo</hi> could obtaine the leſſe at <hi>theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> hand, but was faine to deſire the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of the Weſt, to entreat for what hee deſired; And ſo where B. Iuell made him to entreat but one, it appeareth, he is faine to intreat one to intreat another; in effect two. To coma to the firſt vntruth againe, wherewith hee charged the Reverend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6746:19"/>of <hi>Leos falling on his knees to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Valentinian:</hi> I ſee not in the world how it can be otherwiſe thought but that he did ſo. <note place="margin">Stapl. ut ante</note> Thus the words lie as Stapleton hath ſet them downe: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentinianum au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem imperatorem &amp; Eudoxiam vxorem eius ad memoriam beati Petri, cum multis Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coporum genibus provolutis Romanus Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifex deprecatus eſt.</hi> The Biſhop of Rome beſeeched the Emperour Valentinian, and Eudoxia his wife, at S. Peters Church with many Biſhops kneeling on their knees. Can we by this imagine, that hee kneeled not aſwell as the reſt? I proteſt I ſee it not.
<hi>Leo</hi> himſelfe made the ſuit; <hi>Romanus Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifex deprecatus eſt:</hi> The Romane Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe beſought the Emperour, with many Biſhops falling on their knees. And what can wee thinke but this, that hee fell on his knees as well as they? But what if this keeling bee referred indeed (to put the matter out of doubt) the B. of Rome himſelfe, <note place="margin">Tortura Torti, pag. <hi>167.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Genibus provolutus Romanus Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifex deprecatus eſt.</hi> The Biſhop of Rome falling on his knees, beſought the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour; ſo readeth it a reverend Biſhop of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry late daies. Howſoever it be, Stapleton by his owne evidence doth but wrangle; but by the latter is found a manifeſt deceiver.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6746:20"/>Theſe and ſuch other quarrels, I deſire all ſorts of Readers whatſoever, may bee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, becauſe the <hi>malice of man can never worke the workes of God;</hi> being neither ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall for our purpoſe. Or if I ſhould mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly erre in my tranſlation, miſtaking one place for another, or ſuch other of as ſmall conſequence,<note place="margin">Stapl. ut ante pag. 21. <hi>mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth one place for another.</hi>
               </note> as Stapleton himſelfe did, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he began to tax others, ſaying <hi>Bizan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenus Primas,</hi> the Primate of Bizance (o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe called Conſtan tinople) had been accuſed,<note place="margin">Looke the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants appeale by D. Morton, l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> Sect. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> &amp;c. where indeed, neither had the Primate of Conſtantinople, bin then accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; or doth
<hi>Bizancenus Primas,</hi> ſignifie there the Primate of Conſtantinople (for ſome read it
<hi>Bizacenus</hi>) but it is a word ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from <hi>Bizaceum</hi> a province in Africa, and not from <hi>Bizantium</hi> the cittie of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople. Such overſightes as theſe, may alight on any. But I leaue theſe and come to <hi>Leos</hi> Epiſtles.</p>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Leo the Biſhop, to Theodoſius the Emperour, Epiſt. <hi>7.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THus he beginneth, <hi>Quontum praeſidij Dominus Eccleſiae ſuae in fide veſtrae cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentiae praeparavit, &amp;c.</hi> What ſtrength the Lord hath gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his Church, by means of the vprightneſſe of your Maieſtie, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:6746:20"/>ſhewed by theſe letters which you haue now ſent vnto me,<note place="margin">Rex eſt mixta perſona cum Sacerdote.</note> inſomuch that wee doe reioice, that you haue not onely a kingly mind, but alſo a prieſtlike: ſurely beſides the publike affaires of the Empire,<note place="margin">We place a part of the kings ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy in this. True religion is the roote of all true vertues, &amp; the ſtay of all well ordered co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon weales.</note> your Highneſſe hath a moſt Godly care of the Chriſtian religion, that amongſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, neither ſchiſmes nor hereſies doe grow, <hi>quia tunc eſt optimus regniveſtri ſtatus,</hi> becauſe then the ſtate of your king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes is in beſt temper, when you are ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with the confeſſion of one everlaſting and immutable Trinitie of one Deity. And ſo going on, certifying the Emperour what had hapned at Conſtantinople, touching <hi>Eutiches</hi> a prieſt there whom <hi>Flavianus</hi> the Biſhop had put from the Communion,<note place="margin">Flavianus put Eutiches fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the communion.</note> the cauſe why, the Biſhop of Rome yet knewe not, He commeth to this: <hi>Et quia cauſae me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritum;</hi> And becauſe the neceſſity of the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, the reſpect had to religion, and the laudable care of your Godlineſſe doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it; It is neceſſary that a way bee not given to theſe breaches. But firſt of all wee ought to haue been made acquainted with thoſe thinges whereof <hi>Flavianus</hi> iudgeth <hi>Eutiches</hi> worthy of blame, that of thinges rightly knowne, right iudgement might be given. Thus writeth hee to the Emperour,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6746:21"/>becauſe his brother <hi>Flavianus</hi> Archbiſhop of Conſtantinople, had not certified him of the buſineſſe touching <hi>Eutiches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt 8. Dile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſſimo fratri Flaviano Epiſ copo, Leo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopus.</hi> By this it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, that the Emperour ſate not idle, when theſe buſineſſes were a doing.</note> In the next Epiſtle, hee writeth to <hi>Flavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus</hi> himſelfe, demaunding why <hi>Eutiches</hi> was ſeparated from the Communion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning thus. When the moſt Chriſtian &amp; clement Emperour being of an holy and praiſe worthy faith, carefull for the peace of the Catholike Church, hath ſent vs let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters touching thoſe men, who with you haue raiſed tumults: I marvell that your Brotherhood, whatſoever the offence was, would let vs bee ignorant thereof,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Flavianus inhis</hi> 2. <hi>epiſtle to Leo ſaith he did ſo much to the Emrour.</hi> Et ideò quia dilectio tua de tanta cauſa nos videt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſariò eſſe ſolicitos qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pleniſſime &amp; lucide vniver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſa nobis, quod ante facere ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtinet. <hi>I thinke that this ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in my booke is vnperfict.</hi>
                  </note> and not rather haue provided, that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you the firſt report might haue come vnto vs, leaſt wee ſhould doubt of the truth of thinges done. After this, comming to tell
<hi>Flavianus,</hi> howe <hi>Eutiches</hi> had both delivered his whole declaration of the matter in writing and report thereof beſide vnto <hi>Leo,</hi> he com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth in the ende to conclude thus. And therefore becauſe your lovingnes doth ſee that we are neceſſarily careful of ſo weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie a matter, make haſt to let vs knowe all things touching it, fully and cleerely, as be fore you ſhould, leaſt betweene reports we be deceived with ſome doubt, and diſcord which in the beginning is to bee cruſhed,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6746:21"/>be nouriſhed: ſeeing that reverence remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in our heart God inſpiring it, that the ordinance of our reverend Fathers, which are ſtrengthened from aboue, bee not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved by the naughty dealing of any one.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The letters of Flavianus to Leo.</note> 
                  <hi>Flavianus</hi> now vpon this, according to <hi>Leos</hi> deſire writeth vnto him; Of the ſlights of the Divell, in one Chapter.<note place="margin">1.</note> Of the crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heretickes in another.<note place="margin">2.</note> Of the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies of <hi>Eutiches,</hi> in the third.<note place="margin">3.</note> And of his iuſt excommunication in the fourth,<note place="margin">4.</note> in theſe words. <hi>But not to be long, leaſt I make a long letter, what we haue done formerly, we haue ſent the buſineſſe to your Godlineſſe by letters, in which we haue expreſſed, that he is deprived of his Presbyterſhip, becauſe he is ſo deceived,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Flavianus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated Eutiches before Leo did know it. Then be the all the biſhops of the world lived not vnder the Pope.</note> 
                  <hi>and we haue commanded him not to meddle with the Monaſteries, and wee haue put him from our fellowſhip, that your holynes knowing thus much what is done concerning him, would vouchſafe to manifeſt his impiety to all the Biſhops who liue vnder your holine:, leaſt ſome of them not knowing what hee hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, they may conferre with him as with a right beleever, either by their letters, or ſome other familiaritie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Leo vrbis Ro mae Epiſcop Theodoſio ſemper Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſto.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The ninth epiſtle is againe directed vnto <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperour: where recoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, what he had written vnto him, of his
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6746:22"/>deteſtation of hereſie,<note place="margin">The Pope rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his faith to the Emperour.</note> and his ſtanding firm in the decrees of the <hi>Niceene Councell;</hi> with his accurſe given againſt the impious here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> and of ſome others: he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to this, <hi>Vnde ſi pietas veſtra ſuggeſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni ac ſupplicationi noſtrae dignetur annuere, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Pope deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour that a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell may be held within Italie.</note> Whervpon if your godlines wil vouch ſafe to favour our motion, &amp; ſupplication, that you would commaunde a councell of Biſhops to be held within Italie; all ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals which are raiſed in diſturbance of the whole church will quickly by the helpe of God be defeated, that ſo wee may reioice, when the integrity of the catholike faith thorough all your dominions is kept ſafe, and the Chriſtian peace remaine, and your glory with God be increaſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Caeſari The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoſio religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſiſſmo &amp; pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſimo Augu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſto, Leo Papa Eccleſiae ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicae urbis Romae. <hi>Next vnder God, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours care pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved religion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </note>The 12. epiſtle is directed to the ſame Emperour; wherein hee beginneth thus. <hi>Quantum rebus humanis conſulere provide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia divina dignetur, &amp;c.</hi> How much the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vidence of God vouchſafeth to provide for the affaires of men, <hi>the care of your Maieſtie ſtirred vp by the spirit of God</hi> doth ſhewe; which care of yours, will ſuffer nothing <hi>in the Catholike Church</hi> to be vnappeaſed, or to be vnlike it ſelfe, becauſe the faith which is but one, can in nothing bee different fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſelfe. After this, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6746:22"/>religiouſly loving the <hi>Catholike truth;</hi> for the ſuppreſſing of
<hi>Eutiches,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Emperous called a coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell of Epheſus.</note> did command a councell to be held at <hi>Epheſus</hi> to which councell hee ſent his deputies in his ſtead, to heare the debating of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt <hi>13.</hi> to the Empreſſe Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheria.</note>In the 13. he writeth to the <hi>Godly Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Pulcheria;</hi> beginning thus: <hi>Quantum Praeſidij dominus eccleſiae ſuae praeparavit in veſtra clementia, multis ſaepe probauimus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumentis, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Princes are protectors of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion againſt heretikes.</note> What protection, God hath provided in your highneſſe for his church, we haue ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proved by many experime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. And whatſoever the induſtry of Prieſtes hath effected in theſe times, againſt the withſtanders of the catholike truth hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted eſpecially to your honour; whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt as you haue learned of the holy Ghoſt, you ſubiect all: your
<hi>authority to him,</hi> by whoſe gift, and vnder whoſe protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you rule. After this, he maketh her highneſſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted at large, with the points of <hi>Euti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> hereſie, &amp; telling her <hi>it is a thing wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of her dignitie that error be aboliſhed,</hi> he commeth to tel her,<note place="margin">The Pope would faine haue the day of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell altered but could not.</note> of the time prefixed by the Emperour for the holding of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, ſaith: <hi>Quia ergo multa mihi fiducia eſt, de pietatis tuae ſynceriſſima fide, &amp;c.</hi> Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I haue great hope of the ſincere faith
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6746:23"/>of your Godlines, I beſeech the glory of your cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, that as hetherto by your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devor, the catholike doctrine hath alwaies bin furthered; ſo now you would be an hel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per thereof; which peradventure, it hath pleaſed God to ſuffer to be ſhake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with this temptation, that thoſe who abide in the church might be knowne; the regard to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is not to be neglected, leaſt the loſſe of them become ſorrowfull to vs. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the moſt noble and Chriſtian Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, deſiring aſſone as might be to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound theſe troubles in a councell of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, which he wil haue to meete at <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Emperour called the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell at Epheſus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> hath ſet a very ſmall and ſhort time for their meeting. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> telling her that the Emperour looked for his appeara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce by the day, which he excuſeth, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cludeth with exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto her, that according to her
<hi>accuſtomed care of Religion,</hi> the hereſie of <hi>Eutiches</hi> might be rooted out of the minds of al men. And that if the heretike himſelfe did abiure his hereſie, he might bee recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. 15. Leo Epiſcopus, ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae ſynodo quae apud E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſum.</note>The 15. epiſtle is written to the Biſhops aſſembled at
<hi>Epheſus,</hi> wherin he exhorteth them to condemne the blaſphemy of <hi>Euti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>verum quia etiam non eſt neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da curatio, &amp;c.</hi> But becauſe the healing

<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6746:23"/>of ſuch miſchiefes is not to bee neglected; and the moſt Chriſtian Emperour verie Godly and religiouſly <hi>will haue a councel of Biſhops held,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The iudgement of a councell of biſhops, is better then the Popes.</note> that by a more mature judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment error might be extinguiſhed, I haue ſent thither ſuch as I thinke fit who may in my ſtead bee preſent <hi>at the holy aſſembly of your brotherhood,</hi> and who, with your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent may ordaine thoſe things which wilbe pleaſing to God.</p>
               <p>The 16. is directed vnto <hi>Flavianus</hi> Arch biſhop of <hi>Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinople</hi> &amp; beginneth thus.<note place="margin">Epiſt. 16. Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viano chariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimo fratri, Leo Epiſcopꝰ Romae.</note> I haue received the letters of your beloved<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, together with thoſe things which haue bin done with you, in the matter of faith.<note place="margin">Although there be in his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, no need of a councell yet the Emperour will haue one ſummoned.</note> And becauſe the moſt Benigne Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour carefull for the peace of the church <hi>wil haue a ſynode</hi> called, although it evide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare, the buſines which is to be dealt in, needeth not to be handled in a councel, yet (my beloved brother) I doe certifie you that thoſe will follow, whom in this caſe it pleaſed me to appoint.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. 17. Leo Epiſcopus Theodoſioſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Auguſco,</note>The 17. is to the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius</hi> to the ſame effect, that that before is to the Biſhop; Having received (ſaith he) letters from your clemencie, I perceiue that the whole church hath cauſe to reioice, in that you will not ſuffer the Chriſtian faith, <hi>by
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6746:24"/>which the Godhead is honoured and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, in nullo diſſimilem, in nullo vult eſſe diſcor dem,</hi> to be in none vnlike or diſcordant. A little after this,
<hi>vnde quamvis ad diem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilij Epiſcopalis, quem pietas veſtra conſtituit &amp;c.</hi> And although nothing can fall out, which may giue me any occaſion to meete at <hi>the day of the councell</hi> which your God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe hath appointed,<note place="margin">The Emperour will haue a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, although in Leos iudgement the cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire none.</note> becauſe no exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple can bee brought of any before me, and the leaving of the cittie void will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me: becauſe alſo there is ſuch evident reaſons, that the command of a Councell, needed not haue beene: yet becauſe the Lord God doth vouchſafe to further it,<note place="margin">Then hetherto it was a lawfull Councell.</note> I haue been carefull, that at the time appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, your highneſſe commaundements bee obeyed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> 18 Leo Epiſcopus Pulcheriae Auguſtae.</note>The 18. is to <hi>Pulcheria</hi> the Empreſſe, to the ſame effect that he wrot vnto her in the 13. before, relating what hope the <hi>Church</hi> had promiſed to it ſelfe by her helpe, prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Emperour and her highneſſe that they ſubmitted their ſcepters vnto God,
<hi>by whoſe power and guift they reigned.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Pope ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged that kings raign by God: now the Pope ſaith they raigne by him.</note> A little after. It is a thing worthy of your glory, that errour by theſe meanes be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away. And in the ende excuſing himſelfe for not comming to the councel, telleth her whom
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6746:24"/>hee hath ſent.</p>
               <p>In the 22 Epiſtle written to the Clergie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſtle.</hi> 22. ad Conſtantino politanos.</note> Nobles, and people of Conſtantinople co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of the indirect courſes which hee heard was followed in the councell of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus,</hi> he comforteth himſelf in this, <hi>Sed hos auſus pio &amp; Chriſtianiſſimo principi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidimus minimè placituros.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Popes hope reſts in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming of abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in Councels. The Emperours conſtancy a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne for all. Epiſtle.
<hi>24.</hi> to Theodoſius the Emperour.</note> But our hope is that thoſe enterpriſes will little pleaſe the moſt Chriſtian Emperour. And in the ende hee perſwadeth them to conſtancie by the example of the Emperour, in which hee knew, he would remaine.</p>
               <p>The 24. Epiſtle is directed to the ſame Emperour Theodoſius, in which Leo deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth him, that a ſpeciall Councell might be called within <hi>Italy,</hi> and in no other place, becauſe the ſecond Councell of Epheſus tranſgreſſed againſt the Canons, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the acts were rekoned vnlawfull and void. Thus he ſaith, Behold moſt Chriſtian and venerable Emperor; my fellow Prieſts and my ſelfe, yeelding the duty of ſincere loue towards your Maieſtie, doe beſeech the ſame, before the inſeparable Trinitie of one Diety, and before the holy Angels of Chriſt, <hi>that you would command all things to remaine in that ſtate, wherein they were, vntill a greater number of Prieſts may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6746:25"/>out of the world.</hi> And a little after, <hi>All the Churches that are on our ſide,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">They beſeech the Emperour with teares and ſighes that a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall councell might bee held within Italy but could not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it, who had the ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy then?</note>
                  <hi>all the Prieſts with ſighes and teares beſeech your Gentleneſſe, that becauſe our men haue reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted manfully, and Flavianus the Biſhop hath given his bill of appeale vnto them, that you would command a generall Councell to bee held within Italy, which may ſo remoue all of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, or mitigate them that nothing hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be doubtfull in faith, or any one divided in charitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the 23. Epiſtle which is directed to the people of Conſtantinople,<note place="margin">Epiſtle. <hi>23.</hi> ad clerum &amp; ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopsletanae urb.</note> after he hath largely declared his opinion of the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons debated, he concludeth thus vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Et quoniam oportet vos poſt divinum auxili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, etiam Catholicorum principum gratiam promereri.</hi> And becauſe it behoveth you, next after the divine helpe, <hi>to deſerue the favour of Chriſtian Princes, make your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt humbly and wiſely,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">He prayeth the to be a meane to the Emperour for a Councell. The benefit of a Councell. The Pope had not then all iudgement in the cloſet of his breaſt.</note>
                  <hi>that the moſt cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Emperour would vouchſafe to graunt my humble petition, whereby I beſought him, that a generall councell might bee ſummoned,</hi> by meanes whereof the mercy of God hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thereto, the ſtrength of them that are ſound may be increaſed, and to thoſe that are infected, if they will aſſent to be cured, medicine may be vſed.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:6746:25"/>
               <p>In the 26. Epiſtle vnto <hi>Pulcheria</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſe againſt the 2. Councell of
<hi>Epheſus;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſtle <hi>26.</hi> Leo the Biſhoppe &amp; the holy Synode, which met in the city of Rome to Pulcheria the Empreſſe.</note> he hath theſe words in the very beginning thereof, <hi>Si Epiſtolae, quae pro fidei cauſa per noſtros clericos directae ſunt, ad veſtram pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem perveniſſent.</hi> If the letters which are directed to your Godlineſſe, and ſent by our meſſengers, touching the matter of faith, had come vnto your hands: it is verie ſure, that you could haue given remedy by Gods inſpiration, to thoſe things which were done againſt the faith.<note place="margin">Catholike prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are never wanting to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgate the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike faith.</note> For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were you wanting to Prieſts? When were you wanting to Chriſtian religion or faith? But ſeeing they who were ſent could not come vnto your clemencie, when ſcarſe one of them returned flying vnto vs; we thinke it fit to write againe. And that our prayers may pierce the deeper, wee haue ſent the ſamplers of thoſe writings which haue not hetherto come vnto you, beſeeching you with <hi>Larger entreaties,</hi> that by how much the more thinges are made more bitter, which you ought for <hi>your princely place ſake to withſtand;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Princes muſt haue care of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: if they haue not the he retike wil over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw all,</note> ſo ſhoulde you to your greater glory, haue care of that religion in which you excell, leaſt the ſoundneſſe of the Catholike faith, be violated by any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of humane ſtrife. A little after com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6746:26"/>of ſome abuſes offered at the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell by the Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dioſcorus who was Preſident of the Councell.</note> Wee haue written (ſaith he) (as we could) to the moſt glorious Prince (and which is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt) Chriſtian, of which letters we haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you a copy, <hi>that he ſuffer not the faith into which hee is regenerate and through which by the grace of God hee raigneth to bee depraved by any novelty,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Emperour muſt keepe the Catholike faith whole &amp; ſound Flavianus the Biſhop of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople was depoſed there.</note> becauſe the Biſhop <hi>Flavianus</hi> remaineth ſound in our commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; and ſeeing that no reaſon giveth, that that which was done againſt the order of all our Canons ſhould be ratified: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Epheſine Synod,</hi> tooke not away the ſcandall of diſſention; but increaſed it; by having a councell within <hi>Italy</hi> and time and place appointed;<note place="margin">The Pope would faine haue a councell to bee held within I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly.</note> all complaints, and exceptions of either parties laid aſide, ſo that all things which breed offence, may be more diligently handled againe, and thoſe Prieſts may returne to the peace of Chriſt, without any wound to the faith, or wrong to religion, who through their own weakneſſe were conſtrained to ſubſcribe.<note place="margin">Glad of my furtherance to the Emperour. Looke before Epiſt.
<hi>23.</hi> to the clergy and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople.</note> The which, that we may the better obtain, we pray your Godlineſſe, which to vs is known to be of moſt approved faith, which ſuccoureth the grievances of the Church, <hi>to preſent our ſupplication to the moſt clement
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6746:26"/>Emperour.</hi> ſeeing the meſſage is directed vnto him, from the moſt bleſſed Apoſtle S. Peter, that before this deadly and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiue warre doe wax ſtrong in the Church, <hi>he yeeld meanes by the helpe of God, of renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vnion of Peace,</hi> knowing that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever paines he ſhal beſtow with a willing diſpoſition for the good of the Catholike Church, it will redound to the ſtrength of his Empire.</p>
               <p>In the 31 Epiſtle to the ſame <hi>Pulcheria,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>31.</hi> to the Empreſſe Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheria touching thoſe thing for which he intrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted before.</note> he writeth thus. Your writings haue made much to reioice, and bee glad in the Lord, by which it plainely appeareth, <hi>how much you loue the Catholike faith, and deteſt the errour of heretickes.</hi> But becauſe the divine providence, doth never leaue his Church, as the Lord himſelfe ſaith, <hi>Behold I am with you to the end of the world,</hi> the ſpirit of God, by one and the ſame time and worke, hath kindled the <hi>diligence of your clemency,</hi> and the care of mine heart that in procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring remedies for theſe miſchiefes, both of vs ſhould deſire the ſame thing; for which as before I made ſuit, ſo <hi>nunc quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius peto,</hi> ſo now alſo I craue more earneſtly vſing greater boldneſſe in intreating, after that I haue now received hope by your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, not doubting by the future mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6746:27"/>of God, your clemency working with it but the diſeaſe of wicked errour wilbe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, inſomuch that whatſoever by his aid and inſpiration could bee done,
<hi>will be done with the praiſe of your faith,</hi> becauſe the affaires of men cannot otherwiſe bee ſafe, <hi>except the kingly and Prieſtly authority protect thoſe things which appertaine to an holy confeſſion.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The kings au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie and Prieſtly functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt ioin in one Epiſt. <hi>33.</hi> The Churches hope reſts vpon the Emperour, and he commandeth the Biſhops to ſtand to the Councell of Nice Is not this a part of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy wee ſeeke for?</note>
               </p>
               <p>In the 33 Epiſtle to Theodoſius the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, thus he beginneth. Your Maieſtie hath given vs great hope of quietneſſe in al your letters; but eſpecially now, amongſt all thoſe cares which wee ſuſtaine for the faith, in condemning the councel of Nice, becauſe <hi>you will not ſuffer the Prieſtes of the Lord to goe from it.</hi> And toward the ende thus. And to the ende that a ſpeedier &amp; ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler effect, by Gods helpe might be brought to our
<hi>profitable indeavors by the faith of your clemency,</hi> I haue ſent my Bretheren &amp; fellow Biſhops to your highneſſe, whoſe religion to me is knowne, by whom you may as it becommeth take notice,<note place="margin">They account to the Emperour what their faith is.</note>
                  <hi>what the ſubſtance of our faith is,</hi> according to thoſe inſtructions we haue ſent; that ſo if the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Conſtantinople doe conſent with all his heart in the ſame confeſſion, we may reioice in ſaftie of the Churches peace; and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6746:27"/>that nothing ſeeme to remaine doubtfull, or that peradventure we may nouriſh vaine ſuſpicions. But if any doe diſſent from the puritie of our faith, <hi>and the authoritie of the fathers:</hi> Let your clemency graunt a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall councell to be held within Italy,<note place="margin">Leo and his Biſhops deſire the Emperour for another Councell.</note> as the Synode which is met at Rome for the ſame cauſe, doe deſire with me; that all meeting together, remedies of amendment may bee provided forthoſe that are fallen eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> either through ignorance, or feare: &amp; that hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth it be free for none ſo to mention the <hi>Nicene Councell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Emperour muſt ſee that none violate the Councel of Nice Two religions in one kingdome not to bee ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> as to be found contrary to the faith of it, becauſe it is <hi>Good</hi> for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church <hi>and this your Empire, if one God, one faith, one myſtery of mans ſalvation be held through the world in one confeſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 35. epiſtle is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to <hi>Pulcheria</hi> the Empreſſe, touching thoſe things,<note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>25.</hi> Leo the Biſhop to Pulcheria the Empreſſe.</note> which he requeſted before of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour; wherin after his accuſtomed due prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes given her; And his own deſire to know what the Biſhop of Conſtantinople helde, <hi>in that point of the incarnation of the ſonne of God,</hi> as was meet. He commeth to this. To the obtaining therefore of a ſtaidnes in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions; I haue ſent my brethren and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Biſhops to offer vnto your clemencie <hi>a forme of faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">They offer a forme of faith to the Empreſſe</note> which according to the do
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6746:28"/>of the reverende fathers we preach; which meſſengers after the divine grace it is meete be furthered,<note place="margin">Next and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly vnder God, &amp;c.</note> by the devout helpe of your godlines, leaſt contention trouble the whole church: from which faith if ſome perhaps do diſagree, Let there be a general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell of Prieſts called within Italie, with the conſent gf your highneſſe, whereby all deceipt laide aſide, it may appeare, what things ought to be withſtood, or amended by a longer handling.</p>
               <p>In the 38. epiſtle to the Emperour <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianus</hi> ſucceſſor to
<hi>Theodoſius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 38. Leo Epiſcopus Martiano ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Auguſto.</note> hee writeth, That hee is glad that hee hath received his highnes letters for the good of the church whereof he is ſo carefull,<note place="margin">Martianus ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius.</note>
                  <hi>who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to defend the Catholike faith; from the ſnares of her enemies.</hi> And this hee deſireth his godlines to accept in briefe, promiſing to direct his larger letters in thoſe things which belong vnto his charge, touching the affaires of the church, &amp; the agreement of the prieſts of the Lord.<note place="margin">Epiſt.
<hi>39.</hi> In which he giveth thankes that ſhe by defending of the faith, had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie of Neſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us and Eutiches</note>
               </p>
               <p>The 39. Epiſtle is directed to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Pulcheria, and beginneth thus. <hi>Quod ſemper de ſancta pietatis veſtrae mente prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſump ſimus, id pleniſſimè experiendo cognovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp;c.</hi> That which we did ever perſwade our ſelues of, touching the good intent of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6746:28"/>
                  <hi>your Godlineſſe,</hi> wee know it fully now by experience, which is, that the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith (although it be invaded with the many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of the wicked) yet in your preſence, prepared for defence thereof by the Lord, it cannot be confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. For the Lord doth not forſake the miſtery of his loue nor the deſert of your labor,<note place="margin">The Prince thruſt out the hereticke; and reſtored the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Biſhops that were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placed. both which are acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons belonging to that ſupremacy we ſeeke for.</note> wherby ere while you expelled the crafty enimy of true religion, out of the bowels of the church. This is the ſecond victory you haue gotten, in ſlaying the hereſie of <hi>Eutiches.</hi> It is good therefore to be glad with ioy, and for the proſperitie of your clemencie, to pay my due vowes to the Lord, who thorow al parts of the world where the Goſpell is preached hath gotten you a double crowne, &amp; victory. Let your clemency know thus much, that the whole Roman church doth very much reioice
<hi>in all the workes of your faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In what regard wee ought to haue the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of the Martyres, Read Rainolds de Rom. Eccl. Idol. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>9. §
2.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>2 § 2. Epiſt.</hi> 43. Leo Epiſcopus Martiano Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſto.</note> whether it be in that you helped <hi>our meſſage</hi> with a godlie affection; and that you
<hi>brought back againe the Catholik Prieſts</hi> who were vniuſtly caſt out of the churches; Or in that you cauſed the reliques, of the innocent &amp; Catholike prieſt <hi>Flavianus</hi> to be brought backe with due honour to that church over which hee was ſet.</p>
               <p>The 43. Epiſtle is directed to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6746:29"/>
                  <hi>Martianus</hi> touching the meſſage which in his ſtead he directed to Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inople, for having a councel at Chalcedon; and beginneth thus. I had ſurely deſired of your glorious cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, that the ſynode by vs requeſted, for recovering of the peace of the Eaſt church, which you alſo thought neceſſary, ſhould be a little while deferred till further opportunity; that thoſe Biſhops alſo, might come thether with freer minds, whom the feare of wrong doth withholde. But becauſe with a religious care, you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre <hi>divine things before humane affaires;</hi> &amp; do religiouſly &amp; truely beleeue that it wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be profitable for the ſtrength of your king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, if there be no differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in opinion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the prieſts or diſcorde in the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the <hi>Gospell:</hi> neither do I withſtand your orders, wiſhing that the Catholike faith <hi>which can be but one,</hi> be planted in the hearts of al men. The former Epheſine cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,<note place="margin">The <hi>1</hi> Councell of Epheſus.</note> did iuſtly &amp; deſervedly condemne <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorius</hi> together with his opinion, and who ſoever doth continue in that error, can at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to no hope of pardon. But the ſecond held in the ſame citty cannot be held a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,<note place="margin">The <hi>2</hi> of Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</note> which it is certaine was carried to the ſubverſion of the faith, &amp; which your cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie in loue of the truth, as being good
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6746:29"/>for the catholikes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aliud ſtatue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do caſſabit.</hi> We aske no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſupremacy but this.</note>
                  <hi>wil make voide by appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting an other</hi> moſt renowned Emperour. Therefore I heartilie beſeech &amp; pray your Maieſtie: through our Lorde <hi>Ieſus Chriſt, who is the author and governour of your Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</hi> that you woulde not ſuffer the <hi>faith, which our bleſſed fathers preached as recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the Apoſtles,</hi> to be handled againe as <hi>doubtfull,</hi> in this preſent ſynode; or thoſe things which were of old condemned by the authority of our aunceſters, you ſuffer not to be ſtirred afreſh, by new indeavors. But that you rather command this,<note place="margin">The prince muſt ſtrengthen the Councell by law</note> that the <hi>conſtitutions of the auncient councell of Nice</hi> the interpretations of heretickes being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, may ſtand firme.</p>
               <p>In the 44. Epiſtle to the Emperour again wherein amongſt other things hee giveth him thankes for his defence of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like faith, he writeth thus,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi>
44<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Leo Epiſcopus Martiano Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſto.</note> you haue ſhewd your protection of the Catholike faith, The divine aid doth grow in you,<note place="margin">Pure and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained religion ought to bee the higheſt of all cares appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to publike regiment. Theſe bee points of that ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macywe ſeek for</note> whereby verily not only the ſtate of the Church, but the ſtrength of your Empire is fenced; that ſo o glorious Emperour, you may worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly looke for his protection, whoſe truth you worſhip. For that the ſoundneſſe of my Brother
<hi>Anatolius</hi> was the ſooner ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted. That hee that revived againe the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:6746:30"/>errour long ſince condemned could haue no place in the Church of Chriſt. That the Catholike Biſhops, whom the late perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the heretikes, could not depraue are called backe from their vniuſt exile. And that the reliques of Flavianus of bleſſed memory, were preſerved with due honour his condemner acknowledging his owne impiety; is a title of your vertue, &amp; a fruit of your Godlineſſe, vpon whom I truſt the enſignes of other glories will bee heaped; that as the Church of Conſtantinople, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving received the liberty of the Apoſtolike faith, doth reioice: ſo all men are glad, that all the Churches of your kingdome are cleanſed from the contagion of diveliſh o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions. A little after thus it followeth, <hi>Quae induſtria in omnibus, quae nequitur geſta ſunt &amp;c.</hi> Which labour of ours in amending thoſe things which are wickedly carried, will by Gods helpe take effect ſpeedily; if your Maieſtie vouchſafe to adioine your helpe to the repairing of the Eccleſiaſticall peace; We alſo do deſire that a Synod may be held, as your clemency mentioneth. But that the Biſhops of al the provinces ſhould be gathered together at this preſent,<note place="margin">The Emperour had power to call a Councell ſooner or later as it pleaſed him</note> the neceſſity of the time doth with no reaſon permit. Therefore your clemency may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6746:30"/>it to ſome fitter opportunity. Of which buſineſſe thoſe that I haue ſent can more fully relate vnto your highneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſtle <hi>45. Leo Epiſcopus Pulcheriae Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guſtae.</hi> Not one remedy to all ſorts.</note>In the 45. Epiſtle to the Empreſſe Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheria. After relation of Eutiches blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, he ſaith. But that towardes the perſons of ſuch men an vpright courſe be obſerved and one manner yeelded to thoſe that are amended, and another to thoſe that are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, wee pray your highneſſe to defend them that we haue ſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Apoſtolike ſea, and that you would further that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which wee haue commanded them, that ſo more ſooner and eaſier, the Lord ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vs, thoſe things may bee done which will further your glory and the peace of the Church. Touching <hi>Eutiches</hi> the author of all this wickedneſſe, and ſcandall, I pray your clemency, <note place="margin">Leos power was not able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue Eutiches.</note> that hee may bee removed further of, from that place which is two neere the cittie of Conſtantinople, leaſt he haue more often conſolations from thoſe, whom he hath drawne to his impietie. <note place="margin">Leo deſireth the Empreſſe that a Catholike might be placed in Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oomes which is a part of that ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy we diſpate for</note> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand alſo that ſome Catholike Abbot bee placed in that Monaſtery, where hee very dangerouſly and vnworthily ſate, whoe may deliver that company of the ſervants of God, both from his falſe opinion &amp; can inſtruct them with leſſons of truth.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:6746:31"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>47.</hi> Stapl. abuſeth theſe words, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and right of Peter, or Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſea reſerved referring them as though Leo had the right to call a generall councell: where as Leo ſpeaketh of their decrees that nothing be enacted againſt the priviledges of that ſea. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of vntruths againſt B. Iuell, art. <hi>4.</hi> fol.
<hi>143.</hi> b. &amp; <hi>147.</hi> a. Epiſt. <hi>49.</hi> The Pope deſired that the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell might haue bin deferred but could not. The Pope would not withſtand the Emperour although the Emperor would not al his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt defer the Councell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Epiſtle, <hi>50.</hi>
                  </note>In the
47. Epiſtle written vnto the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> wherein hee exhorteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they would determine of al things according to the ſcriptures; hee faith thus. We muſt imbrace the councell of the moſt clement Prince, which is full of holineſſe, willing your holy brotherhood to meet to gither to overthrowe the crafty deviſes of the divel &amp; ſetling the peace of the church, the honour and right of the ſea of S. Peter preſerved, inſomuch that he alſo invited vs by his letters to be preſent at the reverend ſynod which yet neither the neceſſitie of this time, nor any cuſtome could permit.</p>
               <p>In the 49. Epiſtle to the Emperour <hi>Mar tianus</hi> he beginneth thus. Wee did thinke that your clemencie could haue performed our requeſt, that the preſent neceſſity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected, you would haue commaunded the councell of Biſhops to haue bin deferred vntill fitter oportunity; that ſo, Prieſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called out of all provinces, it might bee indeed an vniverſall councell. But becauſe in loue to the catholike faith, you wil haue meeting to be at this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; Leaſt I ſhould ſeeme to withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <hi>your holy pleaſure,</hi> I haue ſent my legates thither.</p>
               <p>In the 50. to the ſame Emperour thus he writeth. The holy deſire of your clemencie
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6746:31"/>touching the having of a ſynod,<note place="margin">Leo Epiſcopꝰ Mart. Auguſt.</note> for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing of the churches peace, I tooke the more willingly; <hi>and although I did deſire it might haue bin kept within Italie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Pope deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that the Councell might be deferred or kept within I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly; but could obtaine neither.</note> 
                  <hi>and wiſhed that a fitter time had bin ſought out,</hi> that ſo, many mo biſhops might haue bin gathered togither from further regions <hi>yet aſſo one as your letters came, I addreſſed ſome thither in my roome.</hi> And concludeth thus. In reſpect that formerly I haue deſired your Maieſtie to be gracious vnto thoſe, that brought my letters; ſo now alſo I intreate with like aſſurance, that you would be favourable in all things towards thoſe that ſhall be there in my ſtead: whereby thoſe things may the more eaſily &amp; diligently attaine and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome effect, which <hi>are brought into order by your care and ſtudy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>51. Leo Epiſe. Pulche riae Auguſtae.</hi> The Empreſſe had care over the vniverſall Church, Leo could haue no more.</note>In the 51. to the Empreſſe
<hi>Pulcheria,</hi> thus he writeth. I do in all things acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the religious care of your highneſſe, which you do vnweariably beſtow for <hi>the Catholike faith:</hi> And do thanke God that I ſee you haue <hi>ſuch diligence to further the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſall church,</hi> that whatſoever I thinke doth appertaine to <hi>iuſtice</hi> or <hi>loue,</hi> I will boldly moue and ſet forward; that ſo, thoſe things which hitherto haue bin done by the endevor of your godlines without bla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:6746:32"/>may the ſpeedier bee brought to a pleaſing end. In that therefore your clemencie, hath commanded a councell to be held at <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Empreſſe appointed the Councell to bee held at Chalce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, when the Pope would haue had it in Italy.</note> when I made requeſt to you Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie: that it might be kept in <hi>Italie,</hi> that all the Prelates of our part being called, if ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the time would giue leaue, might meete; I haue not taken it vnpleaſantly, but appointed two of my Biſhops to repaire thither.</p>
               <p>Epiſtle 53. is written vnto <hi>Anatolius</hi> the Archbiſhop of
<hi>Conſtantinople,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 53. Leo Epiſcopus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natolio Epiſc</note> wherein hee firſt praiſeth him for his faith in ioyning with the Councell of
<hi>Chalcedon;</hi> then hee expoſtulateth with him, for going about to ſubiect the Churches of
<hi>Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Antioche</hi> vnto his iuriſdiction contrary to the Nicene Councell; ſaith thus. It is not without cauſe belieued, <note place="margin">Flavianus Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople next be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Axatolius.</note> thy predeceſſor of bleſſed memory being caſt out for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Catholike truth, that thoſe that did ordaine thee. contrary to the order of the Canons, ſeemed to conſecrate one like to themſelues, <note place="margin">Anatolius was made Biſhoppe without Leos conſent, yet his ordination ſtood firme.</note> but the mercy of God was preſent directing and confirming thee in this, that thou ſhouldeſt vſe ill beginnings well, and ſhew thy ſelfe not to bee carried with the opinion of men, but with the loue of God, which may very well be ſo taken,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:6746:32"/>if thou looſeſt not the praiſe of that guift with another offence; A Catholike man, &amp; eſpecially a Prieſt of the Lord, as he ought to be intangled with no errour; ſo not to beeled with any ambition. A little after. Therefore after thoſe blame worthy begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, of thy ordinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Biſhop of <hi>Antioche,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration thou challengeſt to thy ſelfe, for which I am grieved, that thou ſhouldſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour to infringe the holy conſtitutions of the Nicene canons, as though this time were only beneficiall vnto the, whereby <hi>Alexandria</hi> ſhall loſe the priviledge of the <hi>ſecond honour,</hi> and the Church of <hi>Antioche</hi> the right of the third,
<note place="margin">So, if all be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to Rome they all ſhall looſe their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours.</note> ſo that theſe places being ſubiect to thy rule, all Metropolitan Biſhops ſhalbee deprived of their honour; which being vnheard of and never before attempted; you are ſo overtaken by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, that you bring the <hi>holy Councell which was gathered together, by the care of the moſt Chriſtian Prince, only to extinguiſh hereſie, &amp; confirmation of the Catholike faith into an occaſion of ambition, and conſtraineſt his ſufferance to thine owne ſide.</hi> A little after O brother, be not high minded but feare, <note place="margin">The Pope fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour as his ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</note> &amp; ſurceaſe to trouble the godly eares of the moſt Chriſtian Princes, with vniuſt Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:6746:33"/>whom I knowe you ſhall better pleaſe with modeſty, then with pride.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 54 Leo Epiſcop. rom &amp; univerſalis Eccleſiae Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiano Auguſt.</note>The 54 Epiſtle is to the Emperour Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianus to the ſame effect that the former was to the Biſhop of Conſtantinople, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in he reioyceth in the faith of the
<hi>Chaloedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Councell,</hi> and further certifieth him of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natolius, who went about in the ſame cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell through ambition to bring vnder him the Churches of <hi>Alexandria</hi> and
<hi>Antioch,</hi> and thus beginneth. Through the great guift of the mercy of God,
<note place="margin">By the care of the Emperour the hereſy was ſuppreſſed.</note> the reioycings of the whole Catholike Church are multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, ſeeing by the holy and religious care of your highneſſe, the peſtilent hereſie that troubled the Church is extinguiſhed that ſo our labour might ſooner come to the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſired ende, which labour of ours. your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie ſerving God in it, hath furthered in faith and power, A little after, I ſpeake to a Chriſtian truly religious, <note place="margin">The Pope is fain to certifie the emperour of the dealing of other Biſhops.</note> &amp; ſound prince: <hi>Anatolius</hi> the Biſhop doth loſe ſo much of his good deſerts, as hee doth deſire to riſe by vniuſt dealing. Let the citty of Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople (as we deſire) haue that which is its due: And the right hand of God ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning you, I deſire that your Empire may be eſtabliſhed in you for ever. And let each man knowe <hi>Propria perdit, qui in debita co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu-</hi>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="17 pages">
                     <desc>〈17 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>

                  <pb facs="tcp:6746:33"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6746:34"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6746:34"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6746:35"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6746:35"/>paſt, according to one faith and meaning; &amp; not to ſuffer them hence forward to be pluckt in peeces by any accuſation. As therefore the mercy of God, by the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of his ſpirit, hath inſtructed the minde of your clemency, firſt of all, provide for <hi>the peace of the Church of Alexandria,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Emperour commands the clergy to chuſe a ſound Biſhop, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Pope belike did not chuſe al.</note>
                  <hi>&amp; per catholicos ſacerdotes talem provideri iubete Pontificem,</hi> and commande that the Catholike Prieſts provide ſuch a Biſhop, in whom for honeſtie of life, and ſoundnes of faith, nothing bee found amiſſe, that all things being rightly caried, the preaching of the truth bee every where kept.</p>
               <p>The 74. Epiſtle to the ſame Emperour hath this tenor; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi>
74. Leo Epiſc. Romae Leoni ſemper Auguſto.</note> Although lately I dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted two letters vnto your Clemency, the one wherof contained the <hi>debt of my ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> the other intreated <hi>for the ſtate of the Church.</hi> Notwithſtanding by an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion which hath offered it ſelfe, God ſo ordering it, it is meete I intreat both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. According therfore vnto that truſt, which by the inſpiration of God you haue performed to the vniverſal Church,
<note place="margin">The Emperour began to deale in Church mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters before any man requeſted him as knowing it to be his duty</note> by <hi>ſet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting in order before any man spake, that which was eſpecially to bee deſired,</hi> we doe not ceaſe to giue thankes to God, and to praiſe his providence in the earneſtneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:6746:36"/>of your faith, who hath withſtood with an holy and Catholike ſpirit (as I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference with my brother &amp; fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Biſhop <hi>Anatolius</hi>) the impude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cies of the heretiks, that we may acknowledge, to the quietnes of the world <hi>that you haue bin a preſerver of the Chalcedon councell.</hi> Which, when it is profitably defined by your ſentence, howe much more careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is it to bee publiſhed to the vniverſall Church,
<note place="margin">Diſturbers of the catholike religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be puniſhed by the magiſtrat</note> inſomuch that ſo the quietneſſe of the chriſtian faith may profit your Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and no hereticall impiety may glory in its enterpriſe? Whoſe craftie ſtubborn contention will forthwith be appeaſed, if it be bridled by the Imperiall power.</p>
               <p>The 75. Epiſtle is alſo to the ſame Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Leo, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi>
75. Leo Epiſc. Leoni Auguſto.</note> where after due congratula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion touching the letters hee receiue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him; and complaint of the impietie of the 2. Epheſine councell which promoted the hereſie of <hi>Eutiches;</hi> Hee commeth to ſay this. What more praiſe worthy, what more religious thing can your Godlineſſe decree, <note place="margin">The Emperour muſt by lawes provide that thoſe thinges which in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſpirituall be eſtabliſhed bee not infringed.</note> then that no man any more be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to <hi>aſſault thoſe things which are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, not only by humane ordinance, but alſo divine?</hi> A little after relating the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the councel of <hi>Nice,</hi> and <hi>Chalce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6746:36"/>it followeth. Before a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Prince therefore, <hi>&amp; one that is to be numbred with due honor amongſt the publiſhers of Chriſt,</hi> do I vſe my chriſtian liberty, <note place="margin">The godly Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour is a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſher of Chriſt.</note> and ſecurely exhort you to the fellowſhip of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Prophets; and that ſtoutly you deſpiſe, &amp; driue thoſe from you, who by their hereſie haue loſt the name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian men: nor ſuffer murtherers, to deale in the faith with a ſacrilegious diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who would by all means make void the faith. For when the Lord hath enri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched your clemency, with the knowledge of ſuch a myſtery, you <hi>ought without delay to conſider: that your kingly power was not given you only for the governement of the world in civill things but especially for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour of the Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sed maximè ad eccleſiae praeſidium.</note> that by repreſſing of wicked enterpriſes you defende thoſe things, that are well eſtabliſhed, <note place="margin">The Emperour muſt reform the Church.</note> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore true peace to thoſe things, which are out of order; thruſting out thoſe who are invaders of other mens right, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the ſeat of <hi>Alexandria</hi> to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient faith, that the anger of God beeing mitigated by your meanes, hee recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence not the <hi>kingly city</hi> for the evils it hath done but remit them. Set before the eies of your heart, renowned Emperour,
<pb facs="tcp:6746:37"/>the prieſts of the Lord, diſperſed thorow the world, <hi>who intreate you for that faith which is the redemption of the world,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in in they ſpecially labour,
<note place="margin">The Emperours ſupremacy is ſeene in theſe things.</note> who being fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of the Apoſtolike doctrine, are chiefe in the church of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with your Maieſtie, not to ſuffer the heretikes, &amp; thoſe that are iuſtly condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned through their own perverſnes, to vſe their owne courſes; ſeeing whether you looke vpon the impiety of their error, or conſider the work of their fury done, they cannot only not bee admitted to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of Prieſthoode, but alſo to haue the name of Chriſtian men taken from them. A little after, after he hath ſpoken of the inſolencies of the heretikes, in exhibiting their petitions to his highneſſe, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to this. It is therefore an excellent thing for your Maieſtie, for that a crowne is added to your Diadem by the hand of the Lord yea to your faith, that ſo you may triumph over your enemies of the Church, becauſe if it be commendable for you to wage war againſt the nations, how great will your Glory bee, if you deliver the Church of <hi>Alexandria,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Emperour muſt deliver the Church fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</note> in whoſe ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, the wrong of all Chriſtians reſts, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a grievous tyrant? Going on, and making
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:6746:37"/>mention of the advertiſement of other matters, he commeth to this
<hi>Sacerdotalem nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> &amp; Apoſtolicum tuae pietatis animum etiam hoc malum ad iuſtitiam ultionis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet accendere.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Emperour had a prieſtly &amp; apoſtolical mind</note> For even this miſchiefe alſo ought to kindle your Prieſtly and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike minde, to the equitie of revenge, which evil doth grievouſly darken the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the Church of
<hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> in which there are found ſome Clerks agree<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing with the heretiks, &amp; even in the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of the Catholiks, aiding by their aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s the parts of the heretiks. In thruſting out of whome if my brother <hi>Anatolius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">If the Biſhoppe neglect his duty, the Emperour muſt reform him and ſettle the Church.</note> who ſpareth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> too favorably, be found ſlowe, vouchſafe you with your authority to adhibit a medicin to that Church, that ſuch may not only be put fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the order of Clerks, but alſo throwne out of the citty, that ſo the holy people of God be no more polluted with the poiſon of perverſe men. <hi>Iulianus</hi> the Biſhop, and <hi>Etius</hi> the Prieſt, who honor your
<hi>godly affection,</hi> I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend with my petition beſeeching you to heare their informations gently for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Catholike faith, becauſe tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they are things of that nature, that they may bee founde profitable for your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:6746:38"/>
               <p>The 78. Epiſtle directed to the ſame Emperour, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 78. Leo Epiſc. Leoni Auguſto.</note> beginneth thus. My mind re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioiceth in the Lord, with much ioy, and great reaſon haue I of reioicing, ſince I know that the moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t faith of your clemencie is increaſed in all things, with the gifts of the heavenly grace; and by the groath of your diligence, <note place="margin">The Emperour had a prieſtly mind. Much good to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the church wrought in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly, by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours meanes.</note> 
                  <hi>I finde the devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Prieſtlie minde in you:</hi> for in all the ſpeaches of your <hi>godlines,</hi> it doth very plainely appeare, <hi>what good the holy ghoſt hath wrought in Italy by your meanes,</hi> and howe much it is deſired by the praiers of all the faithfull, that your Empire may bee inlarged in all glory,
<hi>who aboue the care of your temporall buſines doth beſtow the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of your wiſdome very conſtantly in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spoſing of holy and heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly things,</hi> that ſo the catholike faith which only quickneth mankind, and only ſanctifieth, may abide in one confeſſion; and that diſſentions which are bred out of the diverſity of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane opinions, may be driven away, by the ſoundneſſe of that Rocke, vpon which the citty of God is built. <note place="margin">The city of God is built vpon a ſtrong rocke.</note> A litle after ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of his owne agreement with the church of God againſt heretikes in the councels of <hi>Nice</hi> &amp;
<hi>Chalcedon,</hi> hee ſaith thus: If I build againe thoſe things, which
<pb facs="tcp:6746:38"/>I haue deſtroied, I ſhewe my ſelfe an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, as the Apoſtle ſaith; and bring vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſelfe all thoſe puniſhments <hi>which not only the authority of Martianus a prince of bleſſed memory,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Martianus the Emperour bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of councels with imperiall lawes &amp; penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to which the Pope was ſubiect. The Emperour hath a perfect iudgement to diſcern the truth.</note> 
                  <hi>eſtabliſhed againſt ſuch, but thoſe alſo that I haue confirmed, with mine owne conſent.</hi> After this, giving the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror his ordinary &amp; due praiſes, he ſaith. Now ſince I know reverend Prince, that you are indued with the cleere light of truth, <hi>and to waver in no part of the faith, but are able to diſcern with an holy and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect iudgement, truth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falſhood, and to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver things confuted, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe that are to bee imbraced; I beſeech you blame not my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt, thorough my humility; ſeeing this my taking heed, is done for the whole church, &amp; ſerveth alſo your glory, leaſt in the time of your raigne, the wickednes of the heretikes bee increaſed, or the peace of the Catholikes be troubled.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Emperour by gods grace was ſufficiently furniſhed with guifis of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; pietie, which were his guids in gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Church ſo far forth as we ſpeake of.</note> And therfore although in all things I am aſſured of the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your highnes, &amp; doe <hi>perceiue by the holy Ghoſt dwelling in you, that you are ſufficiently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, that no error can beguile your vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightnes of conſcience,</hi> I indevor yet in this to obey your command, in directing ſome of my brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnto you in my ſteed, who ſhal ſhew you what is the rule of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall
<pb facs="tcp:6746:39"/>faith,<note place="margin">The Emperours ſupremacy in ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleſiaticall cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes is ſeen in this Epiſt. <hi>95. Leo Rom Epiſ. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectiſſimis fratribus, vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſis epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis catholicis per Gall. &amp; Hiſpan. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutis.</hi> At Martianus command skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, who appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which I take is with vs about the
<hi>24.</hi> of Aprill See the differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſpirits. Victor the Biſhoppe of Rome would haue excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated all the Churches in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia becauſe they would not keep the feaſt, as rome did: &amp; now you ſee that Leo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue <hi>200</hi> yeares after him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Euſeb. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> although as I ſaid before, it be known ſufficiently vnto you. And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth thus. Suffer not the lamentable captivity of the <hi>church of Alexandria,</hi> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue any longer, to which by the help of your authority, &amp; vprightnes, her liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ought to bee reſtored, that ſo through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the citties of Egypt the honor of the Fathers, and the prieſtly right, bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired.</p>
               <p>The 95. Epiſtle is written to the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; catholike biſhops through out
<hi>Fraunce</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> touching the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation in the obſerving of the feaſt of Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. <hi>Tantùmme diverſitas iſta permovit.</hi> So much (ſaith he) hath the diverſity ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of moved me, that I opened the ſorrowe of my minde vnto the moſt benigne Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Martianus,</hi> that at his commaund, the truth of it might be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d out with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent ſearch, by thoſe that haue the skill, on what day that holy ſolemnity might beſt be celebrated. By whoſe writing back vnto me, I finde that the determinate time is, <hi>the</hi>
8. <hi>of the Calends of May.</hi> And therefore, thorough a deſire of vnity and peace which I haue, I had rather reſt in the definition of the Churches of the Eaſt, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſſent in the obſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſo great a feaſt.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:6746:39"/>Your brotherhood therefore ſhall know, that the feaſt of the reſurrection of our Lord which is Eaſter, muſt bee kept by all the 8. day of the <hi>Calends of May.</hi> And this by you muſt be certified to other the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that as wee are ioined togither in one faith; ſo wee may keepe the ſolemnity togither.</p>
               <p>In the 99. Epiſtle which is my laſt in this place &amp; for honor of that moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Emperor <hi>Leo</hi> concludeth all the reſt, <note place="margin">Epiſt. 99. Leo Epiſcopꝰ Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oni Auguſto.</note> I finde that thus writeth this <hi>Leo</hi> the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop vnto him. If we ſhould deſire to giue that due praiſe to the glorious purpoſe of your godlineſſe in defence of the faith, as the greatneſſe of things doth deſire, wee ſhould be found vnequal in the matters of giving thankes, if only with the ſlender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of our mouth we ſhould celebrate the ioy of the whole Church. But more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily ſhall the Church it ſelfe yeeld praiſe to your acts and merits, in whoſe buſines you excel, &amp; doe triumph in the wiſhed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent of glory. Let your Maieſtie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore know that all the churches of God are glad &amp; likewiſe reioice <hi>to your honor,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Emperour removed Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus Aelurus, who was choſen after the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Proteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe that wicked murtherer is throwne out of the Church of Alexandria; and the people of God over whom ſuch a miſchievous
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:6746:40"/>robber was ſet, being brought backe to their ancient liberty of faith may be put againe by the preaching of faithful prieſts into the way of ſaluation when they ſhall ſee a whole ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary of poyſon caſt out with him.</hi> Now there fore becauſe you haue done this with an high purpoſe, and heroicall ſpirit; <note place="margin">The Pope deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eth the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>our to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of a catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Biſhop for Alexand. is not this a part of his ſupremacy, to ſee that fit and able men be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for the people of God?</note> ioin this to the finiſhed work of your faith <hi>that you determine of a catholike Biſhop for that cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> which thing will pleaſe God, who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee touched with any ſpot, of the ſo often condemned hereſie, leaſt peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the hidden wound in ſhew, do grow further; and the Chriſtian people, who by your meanes are plainely delivered from the perverſnes of heretiks, be againe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to deadly poyſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Finis, or concluſion is this, Although they bee not all perſwaded that it is the truth which they withſtand, yet that to be error which they vphold—they might vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly the ſooner a great deale attaine to know;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hooker eccleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olitie, l. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that their ſtudy is more to defend, what once they haue ſtood in, then to find out ſincerely and ſimply what truth they ought to perſiſt in for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6746:40"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
